<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Strategy Execution on Michael Brunger</title><link>http://localhost:1313/tags/strategy-execution/</link><description>Recent content in Strategy Execution on Michael Brunger</description><image><title>Michael Brunger</title><url>http://localhost:1313/site-feature-image.jpg</url><link>http://localhost:1313/site-feature-image.jpg</link></image><generator>Hugo -- 0.146.7</generator><language>en-GB</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/strategy-execution/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Finance-Led Business Transformation</title><link>http://localhost:1313/posts/fc-series/finance-led-business-transformation/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/fc-series/finance-led-business-transformation/</guid><description>How controllers can lead change initiatives using Parmenter&amp;#39;s blueprint for business improvement</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1 id="part-7-finance-led-business-transformation">Part 7: Finance-Led Business Transformation</h1>
<p><em>This post continues my &ldquo;learning in public&rdquo; journey as a finance manager. All concepts and frameworks are attributed to their original creators, primarily David Parmenter, Robert Kaplan, and other thought leaders in the field.</em></p>
<h2 id="finance-as-a-transformation-catalyst">Finance as a Transformation Catalyst</h2>
<p>The finance function has traditionally been viewed as a steward of resources and provider of historical information. However, as David Parmenter emphasizes in &ldquo;The Financial Controller and CFO&rsquo;s Toolkit,&rdquo; modern finance leaders are uniquely positioned to drive enterprise-wide transformation.</p>
<p>According to Parmenter, &ldquo;Finance professionals have a holistic view of the organization that few others possess. This perspective, combined with analytical capabilities and credibility, enables finance to lead transformational initiatives that create sustainable value.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This post explores how finance leaders can step beyond traditional boundaries to drive meaningful business transformation.</p>
<h2 id="how-controllers-can-lead-change-initiatives">How Controllers Can Lead Change Initiatives</h2>
<p>The controller role has evolved significantly from its accounting-focused origins. Today&rsquo;s controllers have both the opportunity and responsibility to lead change across the organization.</p>
<h3 id="why-finance-should-lead-transformation">Why Finance Should Lead Transformation</h3>
<p>Parmenter identifies several attributes that position finance professionals as effective transformation leaders:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Enterprise-wide perspective</strong> - Understanding how different functions interact and contribute to overall performance</li>
<li><strong>Data-driven decision-making</strong> - Bringing analytical rigor to transformation efforts</li>
<li><strong>Resource allocation expertise</strong> - Ensuring investments align with strategic priorities</li>
<li><strong>Performance measurement capability</strong> - Establishing meaningful metrics to track progress</li>
<li><strong>Risk management orientation</strong> - Balancing innovation with appropriate controls</li>
<li><strong>Credibility with leadership</strong> - Leveraging existing trust to drive change</li>
</ol>
<p>As Parmenter notes, &ldquo;Finance leaders who remain within their traditional boundaries miss the opportunity to create transformational value for their organizations.&rdquo;</p>
<h3 id="types-of-finance-led-transformations">Types of Finance-Led Transformations</h3>
<p>Finance professionals can lead various types of transformation initiatives:</p>
<h4 id="1-business-model-transformation">1. Business Model Transformation</h4>
<ul>
<li>Evaluating and refining the core business model</li>
<li>Identifying new revenue streams and business opportunities</li>
<li>Analyzing acquisition or divestiture candidates</li>
<li>Optimizing the portfolio of products and services</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="2-operating-model-transformation">2. Operating Model Transformation</h4>
<ul>
<li>Streamlining organizational structure</li>
<li>Enhancing cross-functional processes</li>
<li>Optimizing resource allocation</li>
<li>Implementing shared services or centers of excellence</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="3-performance-improvement-initiatives">3. Performance Improvement Initiatives</h4>
<ul>
<li>Cost optimization programs</li>
<li>Working capital improvement</li>
<li>Productivity enhancement</li>
<li>Margin expansion strategies</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="4-technology-and-digital-transformation">4. Technology and Digital Transformation</h4>
<ul>
<li>ERP implementation or optimization</li>
<li>Analytics and business intelligence initiatives</li>
<li>Robotic process automation</li>
<li>Digital strategy development</li>
</ul>
<p>As Parmenter emphasizes, &ldquo;The most successful finance-led transformations address fundamental business issues, not just finance processes.&rdquo;</p>
<h2 id="parmenters-blueprint-for-a-better-business">Parmenter&rsquo;s &ldquo;Blueprint for a Better Business&rdquo;</h2>
<p>David Parmenter has developed a comprehensive framework for business transformation that finance leaders can deploy. His &ldquo;Blueprint for a Better Business&rdquo; encompasses seven key dimensions:</p>
<h3 id="1-strategic-clarity-and-focus">1. Strategic Clarity and Focus</h3>
<p>The foundation of successful transformation is clear strategic direction:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Mission and purpose</strong> - Defining why the organization exists</li>
<li><strong>Core values</strong> - Establishing non-negotiable principles that guide behavior</li>
<li><strong>Vision</strong> - Creating a compelling picture of the future</li>
<li><strong>Strategic priorities</strong> - Identifying the critical few initiatives that deserve focus</li>
</ul>
<p>Parmenter notes, &ldquo;Without strategic clarity, transformation efforts become disconnected initiatives rather than a coherent journey.&rdquo;</p>
<h3 id="2-customer-centricity">2. Customer-Centricity</h3>
<p>Transformational finance leaders ensure the customer remains central to all decisions:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Customer segmentation</strong> - Identifying high-value customer groups</li>
<li><strong>Customer journey mapping</strong> - Understanding key touchpoints and pain points</li>
<li><strong>Voice of customer programs</strong> - Systematically gathering and acting on feedback</li>
<li><strong>Customer profitability analysis</strong> - Ensuring resources flow to valuable relationships</li>
</ul>
<p>As Parmenter states, &ldquo;Every business decision should begin and end with the customer.&rdquo;</p>
<h3 id="3-process-excellence">3. Process Excellence</h3>
<p>Efficient, effective processes create competitive advantage:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>End-to-end process ownership</strong> - Assigning clear accountability for outcomes</li>
<li><strong>Lean methodology</strong> - Eliminating waste from core processes</li>
<li><strong>Standardization</strong> - Creating consistent approaches where appropriate</li>
<li><strong>Automation</strong> - Leveraging technology for routine activities</li>
</ul>
<p>According to Parmenter, &ldquo;Process excellence is the foundation upon which sustainable performance is built.&rdquo;</p>
<h3 id="4-performance-focused-culture">4. Performance-Focused Culture</h3>
<p>High-performing organizations cultivate distinctive cultures:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Clear accountability</strong> - Defining expectations and ownership</li>
<li><strong>Performance transparency</strong> - Making results visible to all</li>
<li><strong>Recognition systems</strong> - Celebrating and rewarding desired behaviors</li>
<li><strong>Consequence management</strong> - Addressing underperformance constructively</li>
</ul>
<p>Parmenter emphasizes, &ldquo;Culture is created by what leaders tolerate, reward, and punish.&rdquo;</p>
<h3 id="5-talent-development">5. Talent Development</h3>
<p>People are the ultimate competitive advantage:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Leadership pipeline</strong> - Building capabilities for the future</li>
<li><strong>Critical skill identification</strong> - Focusing development on strategic capabilities</li>
<li><strong>Learning ecosystem</strong> - Creating multiple pathways to develop talent</li>
<li><strong>Performance management</strong> - Providing regular feedback and coaching</li>
</ul>
<p>As Parmenter notes, &ldquo;Organizations don&rsquo;t transform—people do.&rdquo;</p>
<h3 id="6-technology-enablement">6. Technology Enablement</h3>
<p>Technology amplifies human capabilities:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Digital strategy</strong> - Aligning technology investments with business priorities</li>
<li><strong>Core systems optimization</strong> - Ensuring foundational systems support the strategy</li>
<li><strong>Data governance</strong> - Managing information as a strategic asset</li>
<li><strong>Digital capabilities</strong> - Building skills to leverage technology effectively</li>
</ul>
<p>Parmenter cautions, &ldquo;Technology should enable strategy, not drive it.&rdquo;</p>
<h3 id="7-measurement-and-governance">7. Measurement and Governance</h3>
<p>What gets measured gets managed:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Balanced scorecard</strong> - Tracking financial and non-financial measures</li>
<li><strong>Leading indicators</strong> - Identifying predictive metrics</li>
<li><strong>Performance dialogues</strong> - Regular discussions focused on improvement</li>
<li><strong>Governance mechanisms</strong> - Ensuring appropriate oversight and course correction</li>
</ul>
<p>According to Parmenter, &ldquo;Effective measurement systems tell stories, not just report numbers.&rdquo;</p>
<h2 id="robert-kaplans-strategy-execution-frameworks">Robert Kaplan&rsquo;s Strategy Execution Frameworks</h2>
<p>Robert Kaplan, co-creator of the Balanced Scorecard and professor at Harvard Business School, has developed several frameworks that finance leaders can leverage for transformation initiatives.</p>
<h3 id="the-balanced-scorecard">The Balanced Scorecard</h3>
<p>Kaplan and Norton&rsquo;s Balanced Scorecard provides a comprehensive framework for translating strategy into action:</p>
<h4 id="1-financial-perspective">1. Financial Perspective</h4>
<ul>
<li>How do we look to shareholders?</li>
<li>Example measures: Revenue growth, profit margins, return on capital</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="2-customer-perspective">2. Customer Perspective</h4>
<ul>
<li>How do customers see us?</li>
<li>Example measures: Market share, customer satisfaction, customer retention</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="3-internal-process-perspective">3. Internal Process Perspective</h4>
<ul>
<li>What must we excel at?</li>
<li>Example measures: Cycle time, quality, productivity</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="4-learning-and-growth-perspective">4. Learning and Growth Perspective</h4>
<ul>
<li>Can we continue to improve and create value?</li>
<li>Example measures: Employee satisfaction, retention, skill development</li>
</ul>
<p>Kaplan emphasizes that the Balanced Scorecard is not merely a measurement system but a strategic management system that helps organizations:</p>
<ul>
<li>Clarify and translate vision and strategy</li>
<li>Communicate and link strategic objectives and measures</li>
<li>Plan, set targets, and align strategic initiatives</li>
<li>Enhance strategic feedback and learning</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="strategy-maps">Strategy Maps</h3>
<p>Building on the Balanced Scorecard, Kaplan and Norton developed Strategy Maps to visualize cause-and-effect relationships between strategic objectives. Strategy Maps show how:</p>
<ul>
<li>Learning and growth initiatives develop organizational capabilities</li>
<li>Enhanced capabilities improve core processes</li>
<li>Improved processes deliver customer value</li>
<li>Customer value creation drives financial results</li>
</ul>
<p>As Kaplan notes, &ldquo;Strategy Maps provide a visual representation of what an organization must do well in each of the four perspectives to execute its strategy successfully.&rdquo;</p>
<h3 id="the-office-of-strategy-management">The Office of Strategy Management</h3>
<p>Recognizing that many organizations struggle with strategy execution, Kaplan proposed creating an Office of Strategy Management (OSM) to coordinate transformation efforts. The OSM&rsquo;s responsibilities include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Strategy development and refinement</li>
<li>Strategy communication and education</li>
<li>Initiative management and prioritization</li>
<li>Strategy reviews and learning</li>
<li>Best practice identification and sharing</li>
</ul>
<p>According to Kaplan, &ldquo;The Office of Strategy Management serves as the architect, process owner, and integrator of strategic planning, execution, and feedback.&rdquo;</p>
<h2 id="project-management-skills-for-finance-professionals">Project Management Skills for Finance Professionals</h2>
<p>Successful transformation initiatives require strong project management capabilities. Parmenter identifies several key skills for finance professionals leading change:</p>
<h3 id="1-project-definition-and-scoping">1. Project Definition and Scoping</h3>
<ul>
<li>Creating clear project charters</li>
<li>Defining measurable objectives</li>
<li>Establishing boundaries and constraints</li>
<li>Identifying stakeholders and their needs</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="2-planning-and-organization">2. Planning and Organization</h3>
<ul>
<li>Developing comprehensive project plans</li>
<li>Creating realistic timelines and milestones</li>
<li>Allocating resources effectively</li>
<li>Identifying dependencies and critical paths</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="3-stakeholder-management">3. Stakeholder Management</h3>
<ul>
<li>Mapping stakeholder influence and interest</li>
<li>Developing targeted communication strategies</li>
<li>Building coalitions and managing resistance</li>
<li>Maintaining executive sponsorship</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="4-risk-management">4. Risk Management</h3>
<ul>
<li>Identifying potential obstacles and issues</li>
<li>Developing mitigation strategies</li>
<li>Creating contingency plans</li>
<li>Regularly reassessing risk profiles</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="5-change-management">5. Change Management</h3>
<ul>
<li>Understanding human factors in change</li>
<li>Addressing resistance constructively</li>
<li>Creating a compelling case for change</li>
<li>Celebrating quick wins and milestones</li>
</ul>
<p>As Parmenter emphasizes, &ldquo;Technical expertise is necessary but insufficient—effective transformation leaders excel at managing the human side of change.&rdquo;</p>
<h2 id="measuring-the-impact-of-finance-led-initiatives">Measuring the Impact of Finance-Led Initiatives</h2>
<p>To maintain credibility and momentum, finance leaders must rigorously measure the impact of their transformation initiatives.</p>
<h3 id="establishing-a-measurement-framework">Establishing a Measurement Framework</h3>
<p>Parmenter recommends a comprehensive approach to measuring transformation impact:</p>
<h4 id="1-leading-indicators">1. Leading Indicators</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Activity metrics</strong> - Are planned actions being completed?</li>
<li><strong>Behavioral indicators</strong> - Are people working differently?</li>
<li><strong>Perception measures</strong> - How do stakeholders view the changes?</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="2-lagging-indicators">2. Lagging Indicators</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Operational metrics</strong> - How have key processes improved?</li>
<li><strong>Customer metrics</strong> - How has the customer experience changed?</li>
<li><strong>Financial metrics</strong> - What is the bottom-line impact?</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="3-return-on-investment">3. Return on Investment</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Cost-benefit analysis</strong> - Comparing initiative costs to benefits</li>
<li><strong>Payback period</strong> - Time required to recoup investment</li>
<li><strong>Net present value</strong> - Discounted value of future benefits</li>
</ul>
<p>As Parmenter notes, &ldquo;The same analytical rigor finance applies to business cases should be applied to measuring transformation outcomes.&rdquo;</p>
<h3 id="types-of-benefits-to-track">Types of Benefits to Track</h3>
<p>Finance-led transformations typically deliver multiple types of benefits:</p>
<h4 id="1-hard-benefits">1. Hard Benefits</h4>
<ul>
<li>Cost reduction</li>
<li>Revenue enhancement</li>
<li>Working capital improvement</li>
<li>Asset utilization</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="2-soft-benefits">2. Soft Benefits</h4>
<ul>
<li>Improved decision-making</li>
<li>Enhanced risk management</li>
<li>Greater organizational agility</li>
<li>Higher employee engagement</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="3-strategic-benefits">3. Strategic Benefits</h4>
<ul>
<li>Competitive differentiation</li>
<li>Market position improvement</li>
<li>Innovation capability</li>
<li>Organizational resilience</li>
</ul>
<p>According to Parmenter, &ldquo;Comprehensive benefit tracking demonstrates the full value that finance delivers beyond traditional accounting and control activities.&rdquo;</p>
<h2 id="case-study-finance-led-transformation-at-a-consumer-products-company">Case Study: Finance-Led Transformation at a Consumer Products Company</h2>
<p>This case study, based on a composite of organizations in Parmenter&rsquo;s research, illustrates the principles of finance-led transformation in action:</p>
<h3 id="background">Background</h3>
<p>A mid-sized consumer products company ($500 million revenue) was experiencing declining margins and losing market share to more agile competitors. The finance team, led by an ambitious controller, proposed a comprehensive transformation initiative.</p>
<h3 id="the-transformation-approach">The Transformation Approach</h3>
<h4 id="phase-1-setting-direction-2-months">Phase 1: Setting Direction (2 months)</h4>
<ul>
<li>Finance team conducted comprehensive performance analysis</li>
<li>Identified critical challenges: excessive SKU complexity, inefficient supply chain, outdated pricing strategies</li>
<li>Developed transformation blueprint with clear success metrics</li>
<li>Secured executive sponsorship for finance-led initiative</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="phase-2-building-momentum-3-months">Phase 2: Building Momentum (3 months)</h4>
<ul>
<li>Created cross-functional transformation team with finance leadership</li>
<li>Implemented Kaplan&rsquo;s Strategy Map to visualize transformation journey</li>
<li>Established Office of Strategy Management within finance function</li>
<li>Launched quick wins to demonstrate value (pricing optimization, procurement savings)</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="phase-3-scaling-impact-12-months">Phase 3: Scaling Impact (12 months)</h4>
<ul>
<li>Deployed SKU rationalization methodology, reducing complexity by 30%</li>
<li>Implemented supply chain optimization based on activity-based costing analysis</li>
<li>Developed customer profitability model to guide resource allocation</li>
<li>Created balanced scorecard for measuring transformation progress</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="phase-4-institutionalizing-change-ongoing">Phase 4: Institutionalizing Change (ongoing)</h4>
<ul>
<li>Established regular strategy review meetings led by finance</li>
<li>Created continuous improvement mechanisms for key processes</li>
<li>Developed capability building program for cross-functional leaders</li>
<li>Refined performance management system to sustain changes</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="results">Results</h3>
<p>The transformation delivered substantial results over an 18-month period:</p>
<ul>
<li>Gross margin improvement of 4.5 percentage points</li>
<li>Working capital reduction of $45 million</li>
<li>15% reduction in operating expenses</li>
<li>Market share growth in core categories</li>
<li>Employee engagement increase from 65% to 82%</li>
</ul>
<p>As the CEO commented, &ldquo;Our finance team transformed from scorekeepers to game-changers by leading this critical business transformation.&rdquo;</p>
<h2 id="self-assessment-finance-as-a-transformation-leader">Self-Assessment: Finance as a Transformation Leader</h2>
<p>Rate your finance function on these dimensions from 1 (strongly disagree) to 5 (strongly agree):</p>
<ol>
<li>Our finance team actively identifies and leads business transformation opportunities</li>
<li>We have a structured methodology for managing transformation initiatives</li>
<li>Finance regularly collaborates with other functions on cross-functional improvements</li>
<li>Our team has strong project and change management capabilities</li>
<li>We quantify and communicate the impact of finance-led initiatives</li>
<li>Our finance professionals understand the end-to-end business model</li>
<li>We use frameworks like Balanced Scorecard to drive strategic alignment</li>
<li>Finance is viewed as a catalyst for innovation, not just a control function</li>
<li>We regularly upskill our team in non-financial business capabilities</li>
<li>Our finance leadership actively sponsors and champions change initiatives</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Scoring:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>40-50: Transformation leader</li>
<li>30-39: Emerging transformation catalyst</li>
<li>20-29: Traditional finance function with untapped potential</li>
<li>10-19: Primarily focused on traditional finance activities</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="action-items-for-finance-leaders">Action Items for Finance Leaders</h2>
<ol>
<li><strong>Assess transformation opportunities</strong> - Identify 2-3 high-impact areas where finance can lead change</li>
<li><strong>Build a transformation toolkit</strong> - Adapt frameworks from Parmenter and Kaplan to your context</li>
<li><strong>Develop project management skills</strong> - Train your team in change management techniques</li>
<li><strong>Create a measurement framework</strong> - Define how you&rsquo;ll track transformation impact</li>
<li><strong>Start small</strong> - Initiate a pilot project to demonstrate finance&rsquo;s transformation capabilities</li>
<li><strong>Build coalitions</strong> - Identify partners in other functions who can support your initiatives</li>
<li><strong>Communicate success</strong> - Share early wins to build momentum and credibility</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Finance professionals are uniquely positioned to lead business transformation initiatives that create substantial value. By leveraging frameworks from Parmenter, Kaplan, and other thought leaders, finance teams can expand their influence beyond traditional boundaries to drive meaningful change.</p>
<p>As David Parmenter emphasizes, &ldquo;The modern finance function must transition from being a reporter of history to a shaper of the future.&rdquo; By embracing the role of transformation catalyst, finance leaders can significantly enhance their contribution to organizational success.</p>
<hr>
<p><em>In what ways has your finance team led business transformation initiatives? What challenges have you faced, and how did you overcome them? Share your experiences in the comments below, and stay tuned for Part 8 of this series, where we&rsquo;ll explore technology enablement for modern finance.</em></p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<ul>
<li>Parmenter, D. (2017). The Financial Controller and CFO&rsquo;s Toolkit: Lean Practices to Transform Your Finance Team. Wiley.</li>
<li>Kaplan, R. S., &amp; Norton, D. P. (2008). The Execution Premium: Linking Strategy to Operations for Competitive Advantage. Harvard Business Press.</li>
<li>Kaplan, R. S., &amp; Norton, D. P. (2004). Strategy Maps: Converting Intangible Assets into Tangible Outcomes. Harvard Business School Press.</li>
<li>Deloitte. (2023). Finance Transformation: Strategic Vision to Practical Reality. Deloitte Development LLC.</li>
<li>McKinsey &amp; Company. (2022). The CFO&rsquo;s Role in Leading Transformation. McKinsey &amp; Company.</li>
<li>KPMG. (2023). The Future of Finance: From Insight to Impact. KPMG International.</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>