<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Finance Leadership on Michael Brunger</title><link>https://michaelbrunger.com/tags/finance-leadership/</link><description>Recent content in Finance Leadership on Michael Brunger</description><image><title>Michael Brunger</title><url>https://michaelbrunger.com/site-feature-image.jpg</url><link>https://michaelbrunger.com/site-feature-image.jpg</link></image><generator>Hugo -- 0.146.7</generator><language>en-GB</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 12:41:15 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://michaelbrunger.com/tags/finance-leadership/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Modern Financial Controller: Series Introduction</title><link>https://michaelbrunger.com/modern-financial-controller-series-introduction/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://michaelbrunger.com/modern-financial-controller-series-introduction/</guid><description>Introduction to the evolving role of financial controllers from technical accounting to strategic business partnership</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-evolution-of-finance-leadership">The Evolution of Finance Leadership</h2>
<p>When I earned my chartered accountant qualification, I envisioned a career focused primarily on technical accounting principles, financial reporting, and compliance. Fast forward to today, and the role of a finance manager has evolved into something far more dynamic and strategic than I could have anticipated. This transformation mirrors a broader shift in the finance profession—particularly for those in controller and finance manager positions.</p>
<p>The days of the financial controller as a mere &ldquo;bean counter&rdquo; are long behind us. Today&rsquo;s financial controllers are expected to be strategic partners, data analysts, risk managers, technology implementers, and forward-looking advisors. We&rsquo;re tasked not just with reporting what happened financially, but with providing insights that shape what <em>will</em> happen next.</p>
<h2 id="why-this-blog-series">Why This Blog Series?</h2>
<p>This blog series represents my commitment to &ldquo;learning in public&rdquo; as I navigate this evolving landscape. As a finance manager with a strong accounting foundation, I&rsquo;m documenting my journey of growth and discovery—synthesizing insights from thought leaders in the field, particularly David Parmenter, whose practical approaches to finance leadership have been revolutionary.</p>
<p>Through these posts, I aim to:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Distill key concepts</strong> from leading finance thinkers into practical, actionable advice</li>
<li><strong>Share implementation strategies</strong> that work in real-world scenarios</li>
<li><strong>Build a community</strong> of forward-thinking finance professionals</li>
<li><strong>Document my own transformation</strong> from technical accountant to strategic finance partner</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="who-is-david-parmenter">Who is David Parmenter?</h2>
<p>For those unfamiliar with his work, David Parmenter is a globally recognised expert in financial leadership, performance measures, and management reporting. His methodologies have transformed finance departments around the world, particularly through concepts like:</p>
<ul>
<li>Distinguishing between Key Result Indicators (KRIs) and genuine Key Performance Indicators (KPIs)</li>
<li>Implementing &ldquo;winning KPIs&rdquo; that actually drive organisational performance</li>
<li>Creating lean, focused reporting that executives actually use for decision-making</li>
<li>Transitioning from traditional budgeting to rolling forecasts</li>
<li>Developing &ldquo;fast close&rdquo; procedures that dramatically reduce month-end processing time</li>
<li>Building finance teams that function as true business partners</li>
</ul>
<p>Throughout this series, I&rsquo;ll be drawing extensively on Parmenter&rsquo;s frameworks while also incorporating insights from other thought leaders such as Jeremy Hope, Robin Fraser, Robert Kaplan, and Jack Stack.</p>
<h2 id="the-transformation-of-the-financial-controller-role">The Transformation of the Financial Controller Role</h2>
<p>The evolving expectations of financial controllers reflect broader changes in business:</p>
<p><strong>Traditional Controller Focus:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Historical reporting</li>
<li>Transaction processing</li>
<li>Compliance and control</li>
<li>Budget variances</li>
<li>Cost accounting</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Modern Controller Focus:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Strategic decision support</li>
<li>Business partnership</li>
<li>Performance optimisation</li>
<li>Predictive analytics</li>
<li>Technology enablement</li>
<li>Creating sustainable value</li>
</ul>
<p>According to a recent survey by McKinsey, companies with strong finance-business partnerships are 20% more likely to achieve breakthrough performance. Yet many finance departments struggle to make this transition effectively.</p>
<h2 id="what-to-expect-in-this-series">What to Expect in This Series</h2>
<p>Over the coming weeks, I&rsquo;ll be exploring:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>The strategic partner mindset</strong> and how to develop it</li>
<li><strong>Performance measurement systems</strong> that drive meaningful action</li>
<li><strong>Reporting transformation</strong> to deliver insights, not just information</li>
<li><strong>Beyond budgeting methodologies</strong> that increase agility</li>
<li><strong>Process improvements</strong> that free up time for value-added work</li>
<li><strong>Building high-performance finance teams</strong></li>
<li><strong>Leading business transformation</strong> from the finance office</li>
<li><strong>Technology enablement</strong> for modern finance functions</li>
</ol>
<p>Each post will combine theoretical frameworks with practical implementation steps, challenges you might face, and metrics to track your progress.</p>
<h2 id="my-learning-approach">My Learning Approach</h2>
<p>As I mentioned, this series is part of my &ldquo;learn in public&rdquo; journey. I&rsquo;m not presenting myself as the ultimate authority—rather, I&rsquo;m sharing what I&rsquo;m discovering as I implement these concepts in my own role.</p>
<p>I invite you to join me in this learning journey:</p>
<ul>
<li>Share your experiences in the comments</li>
<li>Suggest additional resources or experts I should explore</li>
<li>Challenge assumptions and offer alternative perspectives</li>
<li>Propose topics for deeper exploration</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="getting-started-self-assessment">Getting Started: Self-Assessment</h2>
<p>Before diving into the specific methodologies in future posts, I encourage you to consider where your finance function currently stands:</p>
<ol>
<li>What percentage of your finance team&rsquo;s time is spent on transaction processing versus business partnering?</li>
<li>Do your financial reports drive action, or do they simply communicate what happened?</li>
<li>How quickly can you close your books at month-end?</li>
<li>Does your budgeting process add value proportionate to the time invested?</li>
<li>Are your finance team members viewed as strategic advisors by operational colleagues?</li>
</ol>
<p>Your answers to these questions will help you identify which upcoming posts in this series might be most valuable for your situation.</p>
<h2 id="coming-up-next">Coming Up Next</h2>
<p>In our next post, we&rsquo;ll explore the specific mindset and skill shifts required to transition &ldquo;From Bean Counter to Business Partner&rdquo;—examining how traditional accounting expertise can be leveraged to provide strategic insights that drive business success.</p>
<p>I look forward to embarking on this journey with you as we transform our finance functions into the strategic powerhouses they have the potential to become.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>