<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Finance Team on Michael Brunger</title><link>https://michaelbrunger.com/tags/finance-team/</link><description>Recent content in Finance Team on Michael Brunger</description><image><title>Michael Brunger</title><url>https://michaelbrunger.com/site-feature-image.jpg</url><link>https://michaelbrunger.com/site-feature-image.jpg</link></image><generator>Hugo -- 0.146.7</generator><language>en-GB</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 22:42:52 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://michaelbrunger.com/tags/finance-team/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Building a High-Performance Finance Team</title><link>https://michaelbrunger.com/building-high-performance-finance-team/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://michaelbrunger.com/building-high-performance-finance-team/</guid><description>Strategies for developing talent and creating a culture of continuous improvement</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1 id="part-6-building-a-high-performance-finance-team">Part 6: Building a High-Performance Finance Team</h1>
<p><em>This post continues my &ldquo;learning in public&rdquo; journey as a finance manager. All concepts and frameworks are attributed to their original creators, primarily David Parmenter and other thought leaders in the field.</em></p>
<h2 id="the-finance-team-evolution">The Finance Team Evolution</h2>
<p>As finance functions transition from traditional accounting and reporting roles to strategic business partnership, the capabilities and culture of the finance team must evolve accordingly. David Parmenter, in &ldquo;The Financial Controller and CFO&rsquo;s Toolkit,&rdquo; emphasizes that &ldquo;winning finance teams&rdquo; are distinguished not just by technical competence but by their ability to influence business outcomes.</p>
<p>According to Parmenter, &ldquo;The difference between an average finance team and a world-class one isn&rsquo;t just knowledge—it&rsquo;s how that knowledge is applied to create value for the organization.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This post explores how finance leaders can build high-performance teams capable of meeting the evolving demands of modern business.</p>
<h2 id="parmenters-team-development-framework">Parmenter&rsquo;s Team Development Framework</h2>
<p>David Parmenter proposes a comprehensive framework for developing high-performance finance teams, structured around four key dimensions:</p>
<h3 id="1-team-structure-and-roles">1. Team Structure and Roles</h3>
<p>The traditional hierarchical structure of finance departments often impedes performance. Parmenter advocates for a flatter team structure with clear accountability:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Finance business partners</strong> embedded within operational units</li>
<li><strong>Centers of excellence</strong> for specialized knowledge (tax, treasury, etc.)</li>
<li><strong>Shared service centers</strong> for transactional processes</li>
<li><strong>Small, agile teams</strong> focused on specific business outcomes</li>
</ul>
<p>According to Parmenter, &ldquo;Structure should follow strategy—organize your team around the outcomes you want to achieve, not historical departmental boundaries.&rdquo;</p>
<h3 id="2-skills-and-capabilities">2. Skills and Capabilities</h3>
<p>Modern finance teams require a broader skill set than traditional accounting-focused departments. Parmenter identifies several critical competencies:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Business acumen</strong> - Understanding the organization&rsquo;s business model and value drivers</li>
<li><strong>Data analytics</strong> - Ability to extract insights from complex data sets</li>
<li><strong>Communication</strong> - Translating financial concepts for non-financial audiences</li>
<li><strong>Change management</strong> - Implementing new processes and systems effectively</li>
<li><strong>Critical thinking</strong> - Moving beyond reporting to insight and recommendation</li>
<li><strong>Relationship building</strong> - Creating partnerships with operational teams</li>
</ul>
<p>Parmenter notes, &ldquo;Technical accounting skills are the price of entry—they get you a seat at the table. But influence skills are what allow you to make an impact once you&rsquo;re there.&rdquo;</p>
<h3 id="3-systems-and-processes">3. Systems and Processes</h3>
<p>High-performance teams leverage effective systems and processes to maximize productivity:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Standardized workflows</strong> for routine activities</li>
<li><strong>Knowledge management systems</strong> to capture and share institutional knowledge</li>
<li><strong>Performance management frameworks</strong> aligned with organizational goals</li>
<li><strong>Continuous improvement mechanisms</strong> to identify and address inefficiencies</li>
<li><strong>Technology enablement</strong> to automate transactional work</li>
</ul>
<p>As Parmenter states, &ldquo;The goal is to automate the routine so your team can focus on the exceptional.&rdquo;</p>
<h3 id="4-culture-and-mindset">4. Culture and Mindset</h3>
<p>Perhaps most importantly, high-performance finance teams cultivate a distinctive culture:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Forward-looking</strong> rather than historical focus</li>
<li><strong>Solution-oriented</strong> approach to problems</li>
<li><strong>Continuous learning</strong> and skill development</li>
<li><strong>Collaborative</strong> rather than siloed mentality</li>
<li><strong>Customer-centric</strong> orientation (both internal and external customers)</li>
<li><strong>Balanced scorecard</strong> perspective beyond just financial metrics</li>
</ul>
<p>Parmenter emphasizes, &ldquo;Culture isn&rsquo;t just how people behave when everything is going well—it&rsquo;s how they respond when things get difficult.&rdquo;</p>
<h2 id="identifying-and-developing-talent-within-your-team">Identifying and Developing Talent Within Your Team</h2>
<p>Building a high-performance team starts with understanding your current talent and systematically developing their capabilities.</p>
<h3 id="talent-assessment">Talent Assessment</h3>
<p>Parmenter recommends a structured approach to evaluating team members:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Skills inventory</strong> - Document current technical and soft skills</li>
<li><strong>Performance evaluation</strong> - Assess effectiveness in current roles</li>
<li><strong>Potential assessment</strong> - Identify capacity for growth and advancement</li>
<li><strong>Career aspirations</strong> - Understand individual goals and motivations</li>
<li><strong>Learning styles</strong> - Determine how each person best acquires new skills</li>
</ol>
<p>This assessment provides the foundation for targeted development efforts.</p>
<h3 id="development-strategies">Development Strategies</h3>
<p>Based on talent assessments, Parmenter suggests several development approaches:</p>
<h4 id="1-structured-rotation-programs">1. Structured Rotation Programs</h4>
<ul>
<li>Cross-functional rotations within finance (accounting to FP&amp;A, etc.)</li>
<li>Business rotations into operational roles</li>
<li>Project-based assignments to build specific skills</li>
<li>&ldquo;Shadow&rdquo; programs with senior leaders</li>
</ul>
<p>As Parmenter notes, &ldquo;Experience is the best teacher—expose your team to diverse challenges to accelerate their development.&rdquo;</p>
<h4 id="2-mentoring-and-coaching">2. Mentoring and Coaching</h4>
<ul>
<li>Formal mentoring programs pairing junior and senior staff</li>
<li>External coaching for high-potential individuals</li>
<li>Peer coaching networks to share knowledge</li>
<li>Regular feedback sessions beyond annual reviews</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="3-targeted-training">3. Targeted Training</h4>
<ul>
<li>Technical skills training for new tools and methodologies</li>
<li>Soft skills development (presentation, influence, etc.)</li>
<li>Industry-specific knowledge building</li>
<li>Professional certification support</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="4-stretch-assignments">4. Stretch Assignments</h4>
<ul>
<li>Leading cross-functional projects</li>
<li>Presenting to executive leadership</li>
<li>Representing finance in operational meetings</li>
<li>Conducting training for non-finance colleagues</li>
</ul>
<p>Parmenter emphasizes, &ldquo;Development happens at the edge of comfort—provide challenges that stretch but don&rsquo;t break your team members.&rdquo;</p>
<h2 id="creating-a-culture-of-continuous-improvement">Creating a Culture of Continuous Improvement</h2>
<p>High-performance finance teams are never satisfied with the status quo. They continuously seek ways to improve processes, systems, and outcomes.</p>
<h3 id="kaizen-in-finance">Kaizen in Finance</h3>
<p>Borrowing from lean manufacturing principles, Parmenter advocates applying kaizen (continuous improvement) methodologies to finance:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Make problems visible</strong> - Create visual management systems that highlight issues</li>
<li><strong>Standardize processes</strong> - Document standard procedures as the foundation for improvement</li>
<li><strong>Measure what matters</strong> - Establish KPIs for finance team performance (cycle times, accuracy, etc.)</li>
<li><strong>Create improvement mechanisms</strong> - Regular sessions to identify and address inefficiencies</li>
<li><strong>Celebrate small wins</strong> - Recognize incremental improvements to build momentum</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="process-improvement-techniques">Process Improvement Techniques</h3>
<p>Specific tools that finance teams can apply include:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Value stream mapping</strong> - Visualizing end-to-end processes to identify waste</li>
<li><strong>5 Whys analysis</strong> - Drilling to root causes of problems</li>
<li><strong>PDCA cycles</strong> (Plan-Do-Check-Act) - Structured approach to testing improvements</li>
<li><strong>Gemba walks</strong> - Observing processes firsthand to identify improvement opportunities</li>
<li><strong>Standard work</strong> - Documenting best practices to ensure consistency</li>
</ul>
<p>As Parmenter states, &ldquo;Continuous improvement isn&rsquo;t a project with an end date—it&rsquo;s a permanent mindset shift.&rdquo;</p>
<h2 id="jack-stacks-open-book-management">Jack Stack&rsquo;s Open-Book Management</h2>
<p>Jack Stack, author of &ldquo;The Great Game of Business,&rdquo; developed the concept of open-book management, which has powerful applications for finance teams. The approach is based on three core principles:</p>
<h3 id="1-financial-transparency">1. Financial Transparency</h3>
<ul>
<li>Sharing financial information broadly within the organization</li>
<li>Teaching employees to understand financial statements</li>
<li>Connecting individual actions to financial outcomes</li>
<li>Demystifying financial terminology and concepts</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="2-employee-empowerment">2. Employee Empowerment</h3>
<ul>
<li>Involving team members in planning and forecasting</li>
<li>Delegating decision authority with appropriate guardrails</li>
<li>Creating ownership mentality through participation</li>
<li>Soliciting improvement ideas from all levels</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="3-shared-rewards">3. Shared Rewards</h3>
<ul>
<li>Aligning incentives with organizational success</li>
<li>Creating bonus systems tied to measurable outcomes</li>
<li>Celebrating wins collectively</li>
<li>Fostering mutual accountability for results</li>
</ul>
<p>According to Stack, &ldquo;When people understand the business and have a stake in the outcome, they make better decisions and take greater ownership.&rdquo;</p>
<h3 id="implementing-open-book-management-in-finance">Implementing Open-Book Management in Finance</h3>
<p>For finance teams specifically, open-book management can be implemented through:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Weekly financial huddles</strong> - Brief meetings to review key metrics</li>
<li><strong>Visual scorecards</strong> - Prominently displayed performance indicators</li>
<li><strong>Financial literacy training</strong> - Ensuring all team members understand the numbers</li>
<li><strong>Collaborative forecasting</strong> - Involving the entire team in projections</li>
<li><strong>Shared performance goals</strong> - Team-based metrics and incentives</li>
</ol>
<p>As Parmenter notes, &ldquo;Open-book management transforms finance from a mysterious black box to a transparent enabler of performance.&rdquo;</p>
<h2 id="training-strategies-for-upskilling-your-finance-team">Training Strategies for Upskilling Your Finance Team</h2>
<p>Developing a high-performance finance team requires systematic upskilling. Parmenter recommends a blended approach to training:</p>
<h3 id="1-technical-skills-development">1. Technical Skills Development</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>ERP and systems training</strong> - Ensuring proficiency with core tools</li>
<li><strong>Advanced Excel and data visualization</strong> - Building analytical capabilities</li>
<li><strong>Accounting and regulatory updates</strong> - Maintaining technical foundation</li>
<li><strong>Financial modeling</strong> - Enhancing forecasting and scenario planning skills</li>
<li><strong>Process improvement methodologies</strong> - Teaching lean and six sigma techniques</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="2-business-acumen-building">2. Business Acumen Building</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Industry immersion</strong> - Understanding the organization&rsquo;s competitive landscape</li>
<li><strong>Business model training</strong> - Learning how the organization creates value</li>
<li><strong>Strategy sessions</strong> - Participating in strategic planning discussions</li>
<li><strong>Customer exposure</strong> - Interacting directly with external customers</li>
<li><strong>Operational shadowing</strong> - Spending time in key operational areas</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="3-leadership-development">3. Leadership Development</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Communication workshops</strong> - Enhancing presentation and influence skills</li>
<li><strong>Change management training</strong> - Building capability to implement new initiatives</li>
<li><strong>Conflict resolution</strong> - Developing skills to navigate difficult conversations</li>
<li><strong>Project management</strong> - Leading cross-functional initiatives</li>
<li><strong>Coaching skills</strong> - Learning to develop others effectively</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="4-learning-formats">4. Learning Formats</h3>
<p>Parmenter emphasizes the importance of varied learning formats:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Formal classroom training</strong> - For foundational knowledge</li>
<li><strong>On-the-job application</strong> - Immediate use of new skills</li>
<li><strong>Digital learning platforms</strong> - Self-paced skill development</li>
<li><strong>Community of practice</strong> - Peer learning groups</li>
<li><strong>External conferences</strong> - Exposure to industry best practices</li>
<li><strong>Stretch assignments</strong> - Learning through doing</li>
</ul>
<p>As Parmenter notes, &ldquo;The most effective learning combines instruction, application, and reflection in a continuous cycle.&rdquo;</p>
<h2 id="case-study-finance-transformation-at-a-global-manufacturer">Case Study: Finance Transformation at a Global Manufacturer</h2>
<p>This case study, based on a composite of organizations in Parmenter&rsquo;s research, illustrates the principles of high-performance team building in action:</p>
<h3 id="background">Background</h3>
<p>A global manufacturing company with $3 billion in annual revenue had a finance team that was respected for accuracy but criticized for being reactive and transaction-focused. The newly appointed CFO aimed to transform the team into a strategic business partner.</p>
<h3 id="key-challenges">Key Challenges</h3>
<ul>
<li>80% of finance time spent on transaction processing and reporting</li>
<li>Limited business acumen among technically skilled accountants</li>
<li>Siloed structure with poor cross-functional collaboration</li>
<li>Resistance to change among long-tenured staff</li>
<li>Outdated skills with minimal investment in development</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="transformation-approach">Transformation Approach</h3>
<h4 id="phase-1-assessment-and-vision-3-months">Phase 1: Assessment and Vision (3 months)</h4>
<ul>
<li>Conducted skills assessment of all finance staff</li>
<li>Benchmarked team structure and processes against leading practices</li>
<li>Created a compelling vision of the future finance function</li>
<li>Established clear performance metrics for the transformation</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="phase-2-structural-changes-6-months">Phase 2: Structural Changes (6 months)</h4>
<ul>
<li>Reorganized from functional silos to business-aligned teams</li>
<li>Created centers of excellence for specialized knowledge</li>
<li>Established a shared service center for transactional activities</li>
<li>Implemented business partner roles embedded in operational units</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="phase-3-capability-building-12-months">Phase 3: Capability Building (12 months)</h4>
<ul>
<li>Launched comprehensive training program in business acumen</li>
<li>Implemented rotational assignments across finance and operations</li>
<li>Created mentoring pairs between senior and junior staff</li>
<li>Established a finance academy with targeted learning paths</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="phase-4-cultural-transformation-18-months">Phase 4: Cultural Transformation (18+ months)</h4>
<ul>
<li>Introduced open-book management principles</li>
<li>Implemented continuous improvement methodologies</li>
<li>Changed performance evaluation criteria to emphasize business impact</li>
<li>Celebrated and rewarded new behaviors aligned with vision</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="results">Results</h3>
<p>After two years, the transformation delivered significant results:</p>
<ul>
<li>Transaction processing time reduced by 60%</li>
<li>Finance headcount reallocated: from 20% to 60% in business partner roles</li>
<li>Employee engagement scores increased from 65% to 88%</li>
<li>Internal customer satisfaction increased from 3.2 to 4.7 (on 5-point scale)</li>
<li>Finance-led initiatives delivered $45 million in cost savings and revenue enhancements</li>
</ul>
<p>As the CFO commented, &ldquo;We transformed from being financial record-keepers to true business partners driving organizational performance.&rdquo;</p>
<h2 id="self-assessment-how-high-performing-is-your-finance-team">Self-Assessment: How High-Performing Is Your Finance Team?</h2>
<p>Rate your team on these dimensions from 1 (strongly disagree) to 5 (strongly agree):</p>
<ol>
<li>Our finance team is structured around business outcomes rather than functional silos</li>
<li>Team members have strong business acumen beyond technical accounting skills</li>
<li>We have effective systems for sharing knowledge across the team</li>
<li>Our team consistently anticipates business needs rather than reacting to requests</li>
<li>We have formal processes for continuous improvement</li>
<li>Team members regularly rotate through different roles and assignments</li>
<li>Our finance team is viewed as a valued business partner by operational leaders</li>
<li>We have a structured approach to developing team capabilities</li>
<li>Our performance metrics focus on business impact, not just technical accuracy</li>
<li>Our team culture encourages innovation and appropriate risk-taking</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Scoring:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>40-50: High-performance team</li>
<li>30-39: Strong foundation with opportunity for enhancement</li>
<li>20-29: Traditional team with significant development needs</li>
<li>10-19: Fundamental transformation required</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="action-items-for-finance-leaders">Action Items for Finance Leaders</h2>
<ol>
<li><strong>Assess your current state</strong> - Conduct a comprehensive skills inventory of your team</li>
<li><strong>Clarify your vision</strong> - Define what &ldquo;high performance&rdquo; means in your specific context</li>
<li><strong>Identify development needs</strong> - Map the gap between current and desired capabilities</li>
<li><strong>Create learning paths</strong> - Develop tailored development plans for team members</li>
<li><strong>Review team structure</strong> - Align organizational design with strategic priorities</li>
<li><strong>Implement mentoring</strong> - Create formal and informal knowledge-sharing mechanisms</li>
<li><strong>Measure and recognize</strong> - Establish metrics for team performance and celebrate progress</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Building a high-performance finance team is not a one-time project but an ongoing journey of development and improvement. By applying Parmenter&rsquo;s team development framework and Stack&rsquo;s open-book management principles, finance leaders can create teams that deliver exceptional value to their organizations.</p>
<p>As David Parmenter emphasizes, &ldquo;The finance function of the future will be judged not by the accuracy of its reporting but by the impact of its insights.&rdquo; By investing in your team&rsquo;s capabilities, structure, processes, and culture, you can position your finance function as a true strategic partner in organizational success.</p>
<hr>
<p><em>What approaches have you found most effective in developing finance team capabilities? Have you implemented any elements of Parmenter&rsquo;s framework or Stack&rsquo;s open-book management? Share your experiences in the comments below, and stay tuned for Part 7 of this series, where we&rsquo;ll explore finance-led business transformation.</em></p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<ul>
<li>Parmenter, D. (2017). The Financial Controller and CFO&rsquo;s Toolkit: Lean Practices to Transform Your Finance Team. Wiley.</li>
<li>Stack, J. (2013). The Great Game of Business, Expanded and Updated: The Only Sensible Way to Run a Company. Crown Business.</li>
<li>Deloitte. (2022). Finance 2025: Digital transformation in finance. Deloitte Development LLC.</li>
<li>McKinsey &amp; Company. (2021). Building a high-performing finance function. McKinsey &amp; Company.</li>
<li>KPMG. (2023). Future of Finance: Transforming finance for the digital era. KPMG International.</li>
<li>Ernst &amp; Young. (2022). How to build a future-ready finance function. Ernst &amp; Young Global Limited.</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>