<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Modern Financial Controller on Michael Brunger</title><link>https://michaelbrunger.com/series/modern-financial-controller/</link><description>Recent content in Modern Financial Controller on Michael Brunger</description><image><title>Michael Brunger</title><url>https://michaelbrunger.com/site-feature-image.jpg</url><link>https://michaelbrunger.com/site-feature-image.jpg</link></image><generator>Hugo -- 0.146.7</generator><language>en-GB</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 12:41:15 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://michaelbrunger.com/series/modern-financial-controller/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>From Bean Counter to Business Partner</title><link>https://michaelbrunger.com/finance-bean-counter-to-business-partner/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://michaelbrunger.com/finance-bean-counter-to-business-partner/</guid><description>How to transform your role from traditional accounting to strategic business partnership</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-stereotype-vs-the-new-reality">The Stereotype vs. The New Reality</h2>
<p>For decades, finance professionals—particularly accountants and controllers—have battled the &ldquo;bean counter&rdquo; stereotype: detail-oriented, historically focused, compliance-driven, and somewhat disconnected from the operational realities of the business. This perception, while increasingly outdated, persists in many organisations.</p>
<p>As David Parmenter notes in his book &ldquo;The Leading-Edge Manager&rsquo;s Guide to Success&rdquo; (2011), &ldquo;Yesterday&rsquo;s finance team was renowned for producing financial information that was too late, too detailed, and not focused on what matters to the management team.&rdquo; This observation captures the fundamental challenge that modern financial controllers must overcome.</p>
<p>The new reality demands something entirely different:</p>
<p><strong>Bean Counter (Traditional Model)</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li>Focus on transactions and compliance</li>
<li>&ldquo;Scorekeeping&rdquo; mentality</li>
<li>Historical reporting</li>
<li>Technical accounting expertise</li>
<li>Risk aversion and control orientation</li>
<li>Process standardisation</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Business Partner (Modern Model)</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li>Focus on strategy and value creation</li>
<li>Forward-looking guidance</li>
<li>Predictive analysis and scenario planning</li>
<li>Broad business acumen</li>
<li>Balanced risk management perspective</li>
<li>Innovation and continuous improvement</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="parmenters-winning-finance-team-concept">Parmenter&rsquo;s &ldquo;Winning Finance Team&rdquo; Concept</h2>
<p>David Parmenter has been at the forefront of redefining the finance function&rsquo;s role. In his &ldquo;Winning CFO&rdquo; methodology (Parmenter, 2012), he emphasises that truly effective finance teams operate as partners to the business rather than merely as providers of financial information.</p>
<p>According to Parmenter, the winning finance team:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Sells the vision</strong>: Communicates the purpose behind finance initiatives</li>
<li><strong>Creates strategic alliances</strong>: Builds relationships across the organisation</li>
<li><strong>Maintains what&rsquo;s working</strong>: Preserves effective practices while innovating</li>
<li><strong>Understands the customers</strong>: Knows what internal customers genuinely need</li>
<li><strong>Delivers &ldquo;wow&rdquo; projects</strong>: Implements high-impact initiatives</li>
<li><strong>Uses leading-edge methodologies</strong>: Employs best practices in performance management</li>
</ol>
<p>This framework provides a valuable roadmap for controllers seeking to reposition themselves from technical specialists to strategic partners.</p>
<h2 id="the-four-faces-of-finance-leadership">The Four Faces of Finance Leadership</h2>
<p>Building on Parmenter&rsquo;s work, Deloitte&rsquo;s &ldquo;Four Faces of the CFO&rdquo; framework (Deloitte, 2021) offers another useful perspective on this evolution. While originally focused on CFO roles, it applies equally to controllers and finance managers:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Steward</strong>: Preserving assets, ensuring compliance</li>
<li><strong>Operator</strong>: Running efficient finance operations</li>
<li><strong>Strategist</strong>: Helping to shape overall strategy and direction</li>
<li><strong>Catalyst</strong>: Instilling a financial approach and mindset across the organisation</li>
</ol>
<p>Traditional controllers excel at the first two faces but must develop competencies in the latter two to truly function as business partners. As noted in Deloitte&rsquo;s research, high-performing finance teams spend approximately 60% of their time on strategist and catalyst activities, compared to just 30% for average teams.</p>
<h2 id="practical-steps-for-transformation">Practical Steps for Transformation</h2>
<h3 id="1-develop-business-acumen">1. Develop Business Acumen</h3>
<p>Business partnership requires understanding the business beyond its financial statements. As Parmenter emphasises in &ldquo;Winning CFO&rdquo; (2012), finance professionals need to &ldquo;walk in the shoes&rdquo; of operational colleagues:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Schedule regular operational visits</strong>: Spend time understanding how different departments function</li>
<li><strong>Learn the industry language</strong>: Master the terminology and metrics specific to your industry</li>
<li><strong>Study the value chain</strong>: Understand how your company creates and delivers value</li>
<li><strong>Know your customers</strong>: Gain insights into customer needs and behaviors</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="2-build-relationships-intentionally">2. Build Relationships Intentionally</h3>
<p>According to McKinsey&rsquo;s research on finance excellence (McKinsey &amp; Company, 2020), relationship-building is a critical yet often overlooked aspect of finance transformation:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Map your stakeholders</strong>: Identify key decision-makers and their priorities</li>
<li><strong>Establish regular touchpoints</strong>: Create structured opportunities for interaction</li>
<li><strong>Ask better questions</strong>: Focus on understanding business needs rather than just financial results</li>
<li><strong>Speak their language</strong>: Translate financial concepts into business terms</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="3-shift-from-reporting-to-analysis">3. Shift from Reporting to Analysis</h3>
<p>Parmenter advocates for a fundamental shift in how finance teams allocate their time. In &ldquo;Key Performance Indicators&rdquo; (Parmenter, 2015), he suggests:</p>
<ul>
<li>Reduce time spent on data compilation by 40-60%</li>
<li>Increase time spent on analysis by 30-50%</li>
<li>Focus reporting on exceptions and insights rather than comprehensive data</li>
</ul>
<p>This shift requires:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Automating routine processes</strong>: Implementing technology solutions for data collection and basic reporting</li>
<li><strong>Standardising analytics</strong>: Creating reusable frameworks for business analysis</li>
<li><strong>Developing forward-looking metrics</strong>: Building predictive models rather than just historical views</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="4-master-the-art-of-communication">4. Master the Art of Communication</h3>
<p>Business partners must communicate effectively. As Parmenter emphasises in his &ldquo;Winning KPIs&rdquo; methodology (2015), numbers without context rarely drive action:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Know your audience</strong>: Tailor information to the recipient&rsquo;s needs and preferences</li>
<li><strong>Focus on implications</strong>: Explain the &ldquo;so what&rdquo; behind the numbers</li>
<li><strong>Use visualisation effectively</strong>: Apply principles of data visualisation</li>
<li><strong>Tell stories with data</strong>: Frame information within relevant business narratives</li>
</ul>
<p>Research by the Corporate Executive Board (now Gartner) found that finance teams who effectively communicate insights are 24% more likely to be viewed as strategic partners.</p>
<h3 id="5-lead-change-initiatives">5. Lead Change Initiatives</h3>
<p>To be seen as a business partner, finance must actively drive improvement. In &ldquo;The Leading-Edge Manager&rsquo;s Guide to Success,&rdquo; Parmenter (2011) emphasises the importance of leading &ldquo;breakthrough projects&rdquo;:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Identify high-impact opportunities</strong>: Focus on initiatives with significant ROI</li>
<li><strong>Apply project management discipline</strong>: Demonstrate structured implementation capabilities</li>
<li><strong>Measure and communicate results</strong>: Quantify the value created</li>
<li><strong>Build on successes</strong>: Use completed projects as springboards for further initiatives</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="common-challenges-in-making-the-transition">Common Challenges in Making the Transition</h2>
<h3 id="challenge-1-the-technical-comfort-zone">Challenge 1: The Technical Comfort Zone</h3>
<p>Many finance professionals have built their careers on technical excellence. Stepping outside this comfort zone can be daunting.</p>
<p><strong>Solution</strong>: Start small by volunteering for cross-functional projects that allow you to apply financial expertise in a broader context while gradually developing new skills.</p>
<h3 id="challenge-2-credibility-gaps">Challenge 2: Credibility Gaps</h3>
<p>Operational colleagues may be skeptical of finance&rsquo;s ability to add value beyond compliance and control.</p>
<p><strong>Solution</strong>: As Parmenter suggests in &ldquo;Winning CFO&rdquo; (2012), begin with &ldquo;quick wins&rdquo; that demonstrate tangible value to build credibility for larger initiatives.</p>
<h3 id="challenge-3-time-constraints">Challenge 3: Time Constraints</h3>
<p>The daily pressures of financial operations can make it difficult to allocate time to strategic activities.</p>
<p><strong>Solution</strong>: Apply Parmenter&rsquo;s &ldquo;fast close&rdquo; methodology (2013) to streamline month-end processes, freeing up capacity for business partnering.</p>
<h3 id="challenge-4-skill-gaps">Challenge 4: Skill Gaps</h3>
<p>Business partnering requires capabilities that may not have been developed through traditional accounting training.</p>
<p><strong>Solution</strong>: Invest in targeted development in areas like strategic thinking, influence skills, and business acumen through both formal and experiential learning.</p>
<h2 id="measuring-your-progress">Measuring Your Progress</h2>
<p>How do you know if you&rsquo;re successfully making the transition from bean counter to business partner? Consider these metrics suggested by Parmenter and others:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Time allocation</strong>: % of finance team time spent on analysis vs. transaction processing</li>
<li><strong>Meeting invitations</strong>: Frequency of inclusion in strategic business discussions</li>
<li><strong>Decision impact</strong>: % of business decisions influenced by finance input</li>
<li><strong>Satisfaction surveys</strong>: Ratings from internal customers on finance&rsquo;s value contribution</li>
<li><strong>Initiative leadership</strong>: # of business improvement projects led by finance</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="case-study-finance-transformation-at-company-xyz">Case Study: Finance Transformation at Company XYZ</h2>
<p><em>(Note: This is an illustrative example based on Parmenter&rsquo;s work with clients as described in his publications)</em></p>
<p>A mid-sized manufacturing company found its finance team trapped in the traditional model—spending 80% of their time on transaction processing and reporting, with minimal time for analysis or business support.</p>
<p>Following Parmenter&rsquo;s methodology, they implemented several key changes:</p>
<ol>
<li>Automated standard reports using dashboard technology</li>
<li>Restructured the team to create dedicated business partner roles</li>
<li>Implemented a fast close process to complete month-end in 3 days</li>
<li>Established regular business review sessions with operational leaders</li>
</ol>
<p>The results were transformative:</p>
<ul>
<li>Time spent on reporting decreased from 60% to 30%</li>
<li>Analysis time increased from 15% to 45%</li>
<li>Internal customer satisfaction with finance increased by 40%</li>
<li>Finance-led initiatives delivered $1.2M in cost savings</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="self-assessment-where-are-you-on-the-journey">Self-Assessment: Where Are You on the Journey?</h2>
<p>To assess your current position on the bean counter to business partner spectrum, consider these questions:</p>
<ol>
<li>Do operational colleagues proactively seek your input on business decisions?</li>
<li>Can you clearly articulate your company&rsquo;s competitive strategy and market position?</li>
<li>Have you led or substantially contributed to a business improvement initiative in the past six months?</li>
<li>Do your reports focus more on insights and recommendations than data compilation?</li>
<li>How often do you spend time in operational areas of the business?</li>
<li>Can you explain complex financial concepts in non-technical language?</li>
</ol>
<p>The more &ldquo;yes&rdquo; answers you have, the further along you are in your transformation journey.</p>
<h2 id="action-items-for-your-first-90-days">Action Items for Your First 90 Days</h2>
<p>Based on Parmenter&rsquo;s &ldquo;first 100 days&rdquo; methodology for finance leaders (Parmenter, 2012), consider these priority actions:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Conduct a stakeholder analysis</strong>: Identify key business leaders and their priorities</li>
<li><strong>Schedule operational visits</strong>: Spend time understanding the business firsthand</li>
<li><strong>Review your reporting package</strong>: Identify opportunities for streamlining and insight enhancement</li>
<li><strong>Find a quick win</strong>: Identify and implement one high-visibility improvement</li>
<li><strong>Build your knowledge base</strong>: Dedicate time to understanding your industry and competitive landscape</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="conclusion-a-mindset-shift">Conclusion: A Mindset Shift</h2>
<p>The transformation from bean counter to business partner is fundamentally about mindset. As Parmenter emphasises throughout his work, it requires shifting from:</p>
<ul>
<li>Accuracy to relevance</li>
<li>Compliance to performance</li>
<li>Past to future</li>
<li>Data to insights</li>
<li>Control to enablement</li>
<li>Process to outcomes</li>
</ul>
<p>This journey won&rsquo;t happen overnight, but with deliberate focus and consistent action, you can reposition yourself and your team as valued strategic partners rather than mere financial technicians.</p>
<p>In our next post, we&rsquo;ll explore Parmenter&rsquo;s approach to Key Performance Indicators and how to develop metrics that actually drive performance rather than just measure it.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>Deloitte. (2021). <em>Four Faces of the CFO</em>. Deloitte Development LLC.</p>
<p>McKinsey &amp; Company. (2020). <em>The CFO&rsquo;s Role in Helping Companies Navigate the Coronavirus Crisis</em>. McKinsey &amp; Company.</p>
<p>Parmenter, D. (2011). <em>The Leading-Edge Manager&rsquo;s Guide to Success: Strategies and Better Practices</em>. John Wiley &amp; Sons.</p>
<p>Parmenter, D. (2012). <em>Winning CFOs: Implementing and Applying Better Practices</em>. John Wiley &amp; Sons.</p>
<p>Parmenter, D. (2013). <em>Rapid Month-End Closing for Financial Managers</em>. Wiley-Global Finance.</p>
<p>Parmenter, D. (2015). <em>Key Performance Indicators: Developing, Implementing, and Using Winning KPIs</em>. John Wiley &amp; Sons.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Modern Financial Controller: Series Introduction</title><link>https://michaelbrunger.com/modern-financial-controller-series-introduction/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://michaelbrunger.com/modern-financial-controller-series-introduction/</guid><description>Introduction to the evolving role of financial controllers from technical accounting to strategic business partnership</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-evolution-of-finance-leadership">The Evolution of Finance Leadership</h2>
<p>When I earned my chartered accountant qualification, I envisioned a career focused primarily on technical accounting principles, financial reporting, and compliance. Fast forward to today, and the role of a finance manager has evolved into something far more dynamic and strategic than I could have anticipated. This transformation mirrors a broader shift in the finance profession—particularly for those in controller and finance manager positions.</p>
<p>The days of the financial controller as a mere &ldquo;bean counter&rdquo; are long behind us. Today&rsquo;s financial controllers are expected to be strategic partners, data analysts, risk managers, technology implementers, and forward-looking advisors. We&rsquo;re tasked not just with reporting what happened financially, but with providing insights that shape what <em>will</em> happen next.</p>
<h2 id="why-this-blog-series">Why This Blog Series?</h2>
<p>This blog series represents my commitment to &ldquo;learning in public&rdquo; as I navigate this evolving landscape. As a finance manager with a strong accounting foundation, I&rsquo;m documenting my journey of growth and discovery—synthesizing insights from thought leaders in the field, particularly David Parmenter, whose practical approaches to finance leadership have been revolutionary.</p>
<p>Through these posts, I aim to:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Distill key concepts</strong> from leading finance thinkers into practical, actionable advice</li>
<li><strong>Share implementation strategies</strong> that work in real-world scenarios</li>
<li><strong>Build a community</strong> of forward-thinking finance professionals</li>
<li><strong>Document my own transformation</strong> from technical accountant to strategic finance partner</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="who-is-david-parmenter">Who is David Parmenter?</h2>
<p>For those unfamiliar with his work, David Parmenter is a globally recognised expert in financial leadership, performance measures, and management reporting. His methodologies have transformed finance departments around the world, particularly through concepts like:</p>
<ul>
<li>Distinguishing between Key Result Indicators (KRIs) and genuine Key Performance Indicators (KPIs)</li>
<li>Implementing &ldquo;winning KPIs&rdquo; that actually drive organisational performance</li>
<li>Creating lean, focused reporting that executives actually use for decision-making</li>
<li>Transitioning from traditional budgeting to rolling forecasts</li>
<li>Developing &ldquo;fast close&rdquo; procedures that dramatically reduce month-end processing time</li>
<li>Building finance teams that function as true business partners</li>
</ul>
<p>Throughout this series, I&rsquo;ll be drawing extensively on Parmenter&rsquo;s frameworks while also incorporating insights from other thought leaders such as Jeremy Hope, Robin Fraser, Robert Kaplan, and Jack Stack.</p>
<h2 id="the-transformation-of-the-financial-controller-role">The Transformation of the Financial Controller Role</h2>
<p>The evolving expectations of financial controllers reflect broader changes in business:</p>
<p><strong>Traditional Controller Focus:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Historical reporting</li>
<li>Transaction processing</li>
<li>Compliance and control</li>
<li>Budget variances</li>
<li>Cost accounting</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Modern Controller Focus:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Strategic decision support</li>
<li>Business partnership</li>
<li>Performance optimisation</li>
<li>Predictive analytics</li>
<li>Technology enablement</li>
<li>Creating sustainable value</li>
</ul>
<p>According to a recent survey by McKinsey, companies with strong finance-business partnerships are 20% more likely to achieve breakthrough performance. Yet many finance departments struggle to make this transition effectively.</p>
<h2 id="what-to-expect-in-this-series">What to Expect in This Series</h2>
<p>Over the coming weeks, I&rsquo;ll be exploring:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>The strategic partner mindset</strong> and how to develop it</li>
<li><strong>Performance measurement systems</strong> that drive meaningful action</li>
<li><strong>Reporting transformation</strong> to deliver insights, not just information</li>
<li><strong>Beyond budgeting methodologies</strong> that increase agility</li>
<li><strong>Process improvements</strong> that free up time for value-added work</li>
<li><strong>Building high-performance finance teams</strong></li>
<li><strong>Leading business transformation</strong> from the finance office</li>
<li><strong>Technology enablement</strong> for modern finance functions</li>
</ol>
<p>Each post will combine theoretical frameworks with practical implementation steps, challenges you might face, and metrics to track your progress.</p>
<h2 id="my-learning-approach">My Learning Approach</h2>
<p>As I mentioned, this series is part of my &ldquo;learn in public&rdquo; journey. I&rsquo;m not presenting myself as the ultimate authority—rather, I&rsquo;m sharing what I&rsquo;m discovering as I implement these concepts in my own role.</p>
<p>I invite you to join me in this learning journey:</p>
<ul>
<li>Share your experiences in the comments</li>
<li>Suggest additional resources or experts I should explore</li>
<li>Challenge assumptions and offer alternative perspectives</li>
<li>Propose topics for deeper exploration</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="getting-started-self-assessment">Getting Started: Self-Assessment</h2>
<p>Before diving into the specific methodologies in future posts, I encourage you to consider where your finance function currently stands:</p>
<ol>
<li>What percentage of your finance team&rsquo;s time is spent on transaction processing versus business partnering?</li>
<li>Do your financial reports drive action, or do they simply communicate what happened?</li>
<li>How quickly can you close your books at month-end?</li>
<li>Does your budgeting process add value proportionate to the time invested?</li>
<li>Are your finance team members viewed as strategic advisors by operational colleagues?</li>
</ol>
<p>Your answers to these questions will help you identify which upcoming posts in this series might be most valuable for your situation.</p>
<h2 id="coming-up-next">Coming Up Next</h2>
<p>In our next post, we&rsquo;ll explore the specific mindset and skill shifts required to transition &ldquo;From Bean Counter to Business Partner&rdquo;—examining how traditional accounting expertise can be leveraged to provide strategic insights that drive business success.</p>
<p>I look forward to embarking on this journey with you as we transform our finance functions into the strategic powerhouses they have the potential to become.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>