<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Modern Financial Controller on Michael Brunger</title><link>https://michaelbrunger.com/series/modern-financial-controller/</link><description>Recent content in Modern Financial Controller on Michael Brunger</description><image><title>Michael Brunger</title><url>https://michaelbrunger.com/site-feature-image.jpg</url><link>https://michaelbrunger.com/site-feature-image.jpg</link></image><generator>Hugo -- 0.146.7</generator><language>en-GB</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 10:31:52 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://michaelbrunger.com/series/modern-financial-controller/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Lean Financial Reporting That Executives Actually Read</title><link>https://michaelbrunger.com/lean-financial-reporting-executive-dashboard/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://michaelbrunger.com/lean-financial-reporting-executive-dashboard/</guid><description>Creating concise, actionable financial reports using Parmenter&amp;#39;s one-page methodology</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-reporting-paradox">The Reporting Paradox</h2>
<p>Finance teams often find themselves caught in a frustrating paradox: they invest enormous effort into producing detailed reports that executives barely read. A survey by Financial Executives International found that finance departments spend up to 30% of their time on report preparation, yet 65% of executives admit to reading only summaries or conclusions (FEI, 2023).</p>
<p>As David Parmenter observes in &ldquo;Winning CFOs: Implementing and Applying Better Practices&rdquo; (2012), &ldquo;Most finance teams are producing a monthly financial pack that is more like a doorstop than a decision support tool.&rdquo; This disconnect wastes valuable resources and misses the critical opportunity for finance to influence decision-making.</p>
<h2 id="the-parmenter-approach-to-lean-reporting">The Parmenter Approach to Lean Reporting</h2>
<p>David Parmenter&rsquo;s reporting methodology represents a radical departure from traditional financial reporting practices. At its core is a simple but powerful principle: &ldquo;Report the numbers that matter in a way that triggers action&rdquo; (Parmenter, 2012).</p>
<h3 id="core-elements-of-parmenters-reporting-framework">Core Elements of Parmenter&rsquo;s Reporting Framework</h3>
<ol>
<li><strong>One-page reporting</strong>: Distilling complex information to a single page</li>
<li><strong>Exception reporting</strong>: Highlighting only significant variances</li>
<li><strong>Visual impact</strong>: Using graphs, charts, and visual cues instead of tables</li>
<li><strong>Forward focus</strong>: Emphasising forecasts over historical results</li>
<li><strong>Timeliness</strong>: Delivering information when it can still influence decisions</li>
</ol>
<p>As Parmenter states, &ldquo;A finance team should aim to replace their fifty-page monthly report with a series of one-page reports&rdquo; (Parmenter, 2010). This approach aligns with cognitive research showing decision-makers can effectively process limited information at once—typically 5-9 data points (Miller, 1956).</p>
<h2 id="why-traditional-financial-reports-fail">Why Traditional Financial Reports Fail</h2>
<h3 id="problem-1-information-overload">Problem 1: Information Overload</h3>
<p>Traditional reports often provide exhaustive detail, overwhelming readers. Research by the American Psychological Association found that excessive information actually impairs decision quality (Schwartz, 2016).</p>
<p>According to Edward Tufte, information design expert, &ldquo;There is no more powerful way to selectively destroy information than to present too much of it&rdquo; (Tufte, 2001).</p>
<h3 id="problem-2-format-over-function">Problem 2: Format Over Function</h3>
<p>Many reports follow accounting formats rather than decision-making formats. Parmenter notes, &ldquo;Traditional reports are structured for accountants, not for operational decision-makers&rdquo; (Parmenter, 2010).</p>
<h3 id="problem-3-backward-focus">Problem 3: Backward Focus</h3>
<p>Most financial reports emphasise what happened rather than what should happen next. As noted by Hope and Fraser in &ldquo;Beyond Budgeting&rdquo; (2003), &ldquo;Traditional reporting is like driving by looking in the rearview mirror.&rdquo;</p>
<h3 id="problem-4-delayed-delivery">Problem 4: Delayed Delivery</h3>
<p>Monthly cycles create inherent information lags. By the time data is reported, the opportunity for timely intervention has often passed. Parmenter emphasises that &ldquo;A late report, no matter how detailed, is of limited value&rdquo; (Parmenter, 2010).</p>
<h3 id="problem-5-limited-context">Problem 5: Limited Context</h3>
<p>Numbers without context rarely drive action. Research by the Corporate Executive Board found that executives value contextual insights more than raw data (CEB, 2018).</p>
<h2 id="parmenters-one-page-reporting-methodology">Parmenter&rsquo;s One-Page Reporting Methodology</h2>
<h3 id="the-dashboard-approach">The Dashboard Approach</h3>
<p>At the center of Parmenter&rsquo;s methodology is the dashboard concept—a single-page visual summary focused on critical metrics. In &ldquo;Key Performance Indicators&rdquo; (2015), he outlines specific design principles:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>5-second rule</strong>: Key messages should be absorbed in 5 seconds</li>
<li><strong>Trend emphasis</strong>: Show patterns over time, not just current values</li>
<li><strong>Exception highlighting</strong>: Use colour and formatting to flag issues</li>
<li><strong>Standardised layout</strong>: Consistent positioning of information</li>
<li><strong>Forward projection</strong>: Include forecast elements</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="the-report-in-one-page-structure">The &ldquo;Report in One Page&rdquo; Structure</h3>
<p>Parmenter recommends a specific one-page format (Parmenter, 2012):</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Top section</strong>: 3-5 critical KRIs with trend lines (25% of page)</li>
<li><strong>Middle section</strong>: 4-6 exception highlights requiring attention (50% of page)</li>
<li><strong>Bottom section</strong>: Brief narrative highlighting key insights (25% of page)</li>
</ul>
<p>This structure has been empirically tested to match executive information consumption patterns (Parmenter, 2015).</p>
<h2 id="implementing-lean-reporting-a-step-by-step-approach">Implementing Lean Reporting: A Step-by-Step Approach</h2>
<h3 id="step-1-identify-information-needs">Step 1: Identify Information Needs</h3>
<p>Begin by understanding what decisions your reports should inform. As financial reporting expert Randall Bolten notes in &ldquo;Painting with Numbers&rdquo; (2012), &ldquo;Effective reporting starts with understanding how the information will be used.&rdquo;</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Conduct stakeholder interviews</strong>: What decisions do they make monthly/weekly?</li>
<li><strong>Review meeting minutes</strong>: What recurring questions arise?</li>
<li><strong>Analyse information requests</strong>: What ad-hoc analyses are frequently requested?</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="step-2-audit-current-reports">Step 2: Audit Current Reports</h3>
<p>Before creating new reports, evaluate existing ones. Parmenter recommends a structured audit (Parmenter, 2012):</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Volume analysis</strong>: Count pages, charts, tables in current reporting</li>
<li><strong>Usage tracking</strong>: Monitor which sections are referenced in meetings</li>
<li><strong>Time allocation</strong>: Track preparation time for each report element</li>
<li><strong>Decision impact</strong>: Identify which reports have triggered action</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="step-3-design-prototype-dashboards">Step 3: Design Prototype Dashboards</h3>
<p>Following Parmenter&rsquo;s one-page methodology, create prototype dashboards for each major reporting area:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Executive summary</strong>: Overall organisational performance</li>
<li><strong>Operational dashboards</strong>: Department-specific metrics</li>
<li><strong>Project trackers</strong>: Status of major initiatives</li>
<li><strong>Cash performance</strong>: Treasury and working capital</li>
</ul>
<p>Use visualisation best practices as outlined by data visualisation expert Stephen Few in &ldquo;Information Dashboard Design&rdquo; (2006): minimise chart junk, use appropriate chart types, and ensure visual clarity.</p>
<h3 id="step-4-implement-exception-reporting">Step 4: Implement Exception Reporting</h3>
<p>Exception reporting—highlighting only significant variances—is central to Parmenter&rsquo;s approach. Implement this by:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Establishing thresholds</strong>: Define what constitutes a significant variance</li>
<li><strong>Creating alerts</strong>: Develop visual indicators for exceptions</li>
<li><strong>Automating detection</strong>: Use technology to flag exceptions automatically</li>
</ul>
<p>As Parmenter emphasises, &ldquo;Executives don&rsquo;t need to know everything is fine—they need to know what requires their attention&rdquo; (Parmenter, 2012).</p>
<h3 id="step-5-build-forecasting-elements">Step 5: Build Forecasting Elements</h3>
<p>Expand reporting from historical focus to include forward-looking elements. According to Steve Player and Steve Morlidge in &ldquo;Future Ready&rdquo; (2010), effective forecasts share these characteristics:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Rolling horizon</strong>: Always maintain same forecast distance</li>
<li><strong>Driver-based</strong>: Built on operational rather than financial drivers</li>
<li><strong>Scenario-enabled</strong>: Show range of possible outcomes</li>
<li><strong>Frequently updated</strong>: Refresh as new information becomes available</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="step-6-create-delivery-cadence">Step 6: Create Delivery Cadence</h3>
<p>Implement appropriate reporting frequencies based on metric volatility and decision timelines. Parmenter suggests (2015):</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Daily</strong>: Critical operational metrics (production, sales, cash)</li>
<li><strong>Weekly</strong>: Performance indicators and project status</li>
<li><strong>Monthly</strong>: KRIs and financial summaries</li>
<li><strong>Quarterly</strong>: Strategic reviews and trend analysis</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="step-7-continuously-improve">Step 7: Continuously Improve</h3>
<p>Implement a formal feedback mechanism to refine reporting. As Parmenter notes, &ldquo;The perfect dashboard is never created on the first attempt&rdquo; (Parmenter, 2012).</p>
<h2 id="case-study-transforming-financial-reporting-at-a-retail-chain">Case Study: Transforming Financial Reporting at a Retail Chain</h2>
<p><em>(Note: This case study is adapted from examples in Parmenter&rsquo;s publications)</em></p>
<p>A multi-location retail business struggled with information overload. Their monthly reporting package exceeded 45 pages and took 15 days to produce after month-end. Following Parmenter&rsquo;s methodology:</p>
<ol>
<li>They interviewed key decision-makers about information needs</li>
<li>Created three one-page dashboards (executive, store operations, inventory)</li>
<li>Implemented a 3-tier reporting system:
<ul>
<li>Daily sales and inventory report (automated)</li>
<li>Weekly performance dashboard (Tuesday delivery)</li>
<li>Monthly executive summary (5 days after month-end)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Results after implementation:</p>
<ul>
<li>Report preparation time decreased by 70%</li>
<li>Executive engagement with financial information increased</li>
<li>Decision response time improved from weeks to days</li>
<li>Finance team redirected 25 hours per month to analysis</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="visual-design-principles-for-financial-information">Visual Design Principles for Financial Information</h2>
<p>Effective reporting isn&rsquo;t just about content—it&rsquo;s about presentation. Drawing from Edward Tufte&rsquo;s &ldquo;Visual Display of Quantitative Information&rdquo; (2001) and Stephen Few&rsquo;s work, consider these design principles:</p>
<h3 id="1-signal-to-noise-ratio">1. Signal-to-Noise Ratio</h3>
<p>Eliminate what Tufte calls &ldquo;chart junk&rdquo;—decorative elements that don&rsquo;t convey information:</p>
<ul>
<li>Remove grid lines unless essential</li>
<li>Eliminate 3D effects</li>
<li>Minimise text labels</li>
<li>Use subtle background colours if any</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="2-choose-appropriate-chart-types">2. Choose Appropriate Chart Types</h3>
<p>Different data requires different visualisation:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Time series</strong>: Line charts</li>
<li><strong>Composition</strong>: Stacked bar charts</li>
<li><strong>Comparison</strong>: Side-by-side bars</li>
<li><strong>Correlation</strong>: Scatter plots</li>
<li><strong>Distribution</strong>: Histograms</li>
</ul>
<p>As Few notes, &ldquo;The most common reporting mistake is using the wrong chart type for the data&rdquo; (Few, 2006).</p>
<h3 id="3-colour-psychology">3. Colour Psychology</h3>
<p>Use colour strategically:</p>
<ul>
<li>Red/yellow/green for performance indicators</li>
<li>Blue for neutral information</li>
<li>Consistent colour scheme across all reports</li>
<li>No more than 5-7 colours total</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="4-typography-matters">4. Typography Matters</h3>
<p>Text elements should enhance readability:</p>
<ul>
<li>Use sans-serif fonts for screen display</li>
<li>Establish clear hierarchy with font sizes</li>
<li>Left-align most text</li>
<li>Right-align numbers for comparison</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="technology-enablers-for-lean-reporting">Technology Enablers for Lean Reporting</h2>
<p>Modern tools make Parmenter&rsquo;s approach more achievable than ever:</p>
<h3 id="data-visualisation-software">Data Visualisation Software</h3>
<p>Tools like Tableau, Power BI, and Qlik provide:</p>
<ul>
<li>Interactive dashboards</li>
<li>Data exploration capabilities</li>
<li>Automated refreshes</li>
<li>Exception highlighting</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="cloud-based-analytics">Cloud-Based Analytics</h3>
<p>Cloud platforms offer advantages for distributed organisations:</p>
<ul>
<li>Real-time data access</li>
<li>Mobile compatibility</li>
<li>Collaborative analysis</li>
<li>Centralised data governance</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="automated-data-integration">Automated Data Integration</h3>
<p>ETL (Extract, Transform, Load) tools reduce manual effort:</p>
<ul>
<li>Scheduled data refreshes</li>
<li>Cross-system integration</li>
<li>Data cleansing automation</li>
<li>Validation rules</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="the-financial-controllers-role-in-reporting-transformation">The Financial Controller&rsquo;s Role in Reporting Transformation</h2>
<p>As financial controller, you are uniquely positioned to lead this transformation:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Challenge the status quo</strong>: Question every report and every page</li>
<li><strong>Champion clarity</strong>: Advocate for users who need actionable information</li>
<li><strong>Bridge functions</strong>: Connect financial data to operational context</li>
<li><strong>Implement standards</strong>: Create reporting templates and guidelines</li>
<li><strong>Measure impact</strong>: Track how reporting changes influence decisions</li>
</ol>
<p>As Parmenter emphasises in &ldquo;The Leading-Edge Manager&rsquo;s Guide to Success&rdquo; (2011), &ldquo;The finance team should be the organisation&rsquo;s leader in information presentation.&rdquo;</p>
<h2 id="common-implementation-challenges">Common Implementation Challenges</h2>
<h3 id="challenge-1-the-more-detail-mindset">Challenge 1: The &ldquo;More Detail&rdquo; Mindset</h3>
<p>Some stakeholders believe more information is always better.</p>
<p><strong>Solution</strong>: Parmenter suggests creating a &ldquo;drill-down&rdquo; capability—maintain the one-page summary but enable access to supporting detail on request.</p>
<h3 id="challenge-2-weve-always-done-it-this-way">Challenge 2: &ldquo;We&rsquo;ve Always Done It This Way&rdquo;</h3>
<p>Organisational inertia often preserves ineffective reporting.</p>
<p><strong>Solution</strong>: Implement pilot projects with receptive stakeholders to demonstrate value, then use success stories to drive broader adoption.</p>
<h3 id="challenge-3-system-limitations">Challenge 3: System Limitations</h3>
<p>Legacy systems may not support modern visualisation.</p>
<p><strong>Solution</strong>: Begin with manual dashboard creation while building the case for technology investment based on time savings.</p>
<h3 id="challenge-4-skill-gaps">Challenge 4: Skill Gaps</h3>
<p>Many finance teams lack data visualisation expertise.</p>
<p><strong>Solution</strong>: Invest in targeted training on visualisation principles and tools. As Parmenter notes, &ldquo;This skill development pays immediate dividends&rdquo; (Parmenter, 2012).</p>
<h2 id="self-assessment-how-lean-is-your-reporting">Self-Assessment: How Lean Is Your Reporting?</h2>
<p>Evaluate your current reporting against these criteria:</p>
<ol>
<li>How many pages is your primary monthly financial report?</li>
<li>What percentage of reported metrics are discussed in management meetings?</li>
<li>How many days after period-end is your reporting available?</li>
<li>What ratio of charts/graphics to tables exists in your reporting?</li>
<li>Do your reports contain forward-looking elements?</li>
<li>How often are reports actually referenced for decisions?</li>
</ol>
<p>The more your answers diverge from Parmenter&rsquo;s recommendations, the greater your opportunity for improvement.</p>
<h2 id="action-plan-for-your-next-60-days">Action Plan for Your Next 60 Days</h2>
<p>Based on Parmenter&rsquo;s implementation methodology (2012), consider these immediate actions:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Select one critical report</strong> to transform as a pilot</li>
<li><strong>Interview three key users</strong> about their information needs</li>
<li><strong>Create a one-page prototype</strong> using the Parmenter structure</li>
<li><strong>Run parallel reporting</strong> (old and new) for one cycle</li>
<li><strong>Gather feedback</strong> and refine</li>
<li><strong>Document time savings</strong> and decision impact</li>
<li><strong>Extend approach</strong> to additional reports</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="conclusion-from-reporting-to-insight">Conclusion: From Reporting to Insight</h2>
<p>The transformation from traditional reporting to Parmenter&rsquo;s lean approach represents a fundamental shift in how finance delivers value. As he notes, &ldquo;It&rsquo;s not about producing less information—it&rsquo;s about producing more insight&rdquo; (Parmenter, 2015).</p>
<p>By embracing these principles, financial controllers can escape the reporting treadmill and position finance as a true source of decision support.</p>
<p>In our next post, we&rsquo;ll explore how to move beyond traditional budgeting to implement rolling forecasts that increase organisational agility and improve resource allocation.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>Bolten, R. (2012). <em>Painting with Numbers: Presenting Financials and Other Numbers So People Will Understand You</em>. Wiley.</p>
<p>Corporate Executive Board (CEB). (2018). <em>Finance Function Effectiveness Survey</em>. Gartner.</p>
<p>Few, S. (2006). <em>Information Dashboard Design: The Effective Visual Communication of Data</em>. O&rsquo;Reilly Media.</p>
<p>Financial Executives International (FEI). (2023). <em>Financial Reporting Practices Survey</em>. Financial Executives Research Foundation.</p>
<p>Hope, J., &amp; Fraser, R. (2003). <em>Beyond Budgeting: How Managers Can Break Free from the Annual Performance Trap</em>. Harvard Business Press.</p>
<p>Miller, G. A. (1956). The magical number seven, plus or minus two: Some limits on our capacity for processing information. <em>Psychological Review, 63</em>(2), 81–97.</p>
<p>Parmenter, D. (2010). <em>Key Performance Indicators: Developing, Implementing, and Using Winning KPIs (2nd ed.)</em>. John Wiley &amp; Sons.</p>
<p>Parmenter, D. (2011). <em>The Leading-Edge Manager&rsquo;s Guide to Success: Strategies and Better Practices</em>. John Wiley &amp; Sons.</p>
<p>Parmenter, D. (2012). <em>Winning CFOs: Implementing and Applying Better Practices</em>. John Wiley &amp; Sons.</p>
<p>Parmenter, D. (2015). <em>Key Performance Indicators: Developing, Implementing, and Using Winning KPIs (3rd ed.)</em>. John Wiley &amp; Sons.</p>
<p>Player, S., &amp; Morlidge, S. (2010). <em>Future Ready: How to Master Business Forecasting</em>. Wiley.</p>
<p>Schwartz, B. (2016). The Paradox of Choice: Why More Is Less. <em>Ecco Press</em>.</p>
<p>Tufte, E. R. (2001). <em>The Visual Display of Quantitative Information (2nd ed.)</em>. Graphics Press.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>KPIs That Actually Drive Performance</title><link>https://michaelbrunger.com/effective-kpis-drive-business-performance/</link><pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://michaelbrunger.com/effective-kpis-drive-business-performance/</guid><description>Implementing effective KPIs using David Parmenter&amp;#39;s methodology for meaningful performance measurement</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-kpi-crisis-in-modern-business">The KPI Crisis in Modern Business</h2>
<p>Most organisations are drowning in metrics while starving for insight. According to research by MIT Sloan Management Review, over 70% of executives believe their KPI systems don&rsquo;t provide the strategic guidance they need (Neely &amp; Bourne, 2020). This disconnect illustrates a fundamental problem: despite the prevalence of performance measurement systems, few organisations have metrics that genuinely drive improvement.</p>
<p>As David Parmenter explains in his seminal work &ldquo;Key Performance Indicators: Developing, Implementing, and Using Winning KPIs&rdquo; (2015), &ldquo;Most organisations have been measuring the wrong things in the wrong way.&rdquo; The result is what he calls &ldquo;measurement dysfunction&rdquo;—where metrics create perverse incentives, drive suboptimal behaviors, or simply fail to influence performance at all.</p>
<h2 id="parmenters-revolutionary-kpi-framework">Parmenter&rsquo;s Revolutionary KPI Framework</h2>
<p>What makes Parmenter&rsquo;s approach revolutionary is his fundamental reclassification of performance measures. Unlike traditional approaches that treat all metrics as &ldquo;KPIs,&rdquo; Parmenter establishes a clear taxonomy:</p>
<h3 id="the-four-types-of-performance-measures">The Four Types of Performance Measures</h3>
<ol>
<li><strong>Key Result Indicators (KRIs)</strong>: High-level measures that tell the board how management has performed in a critical success factor or perspective</li>
<li><strong>Result Indicators (RIs)</strong>: Tell you what you have done</li>
<li><strong>Performance Indicators (PIs)</strong>: Tell you what to do</li>
<li><strong>Key Performance Indicators (KPIs)</strong>: Tell you what to do to increase performance dramatically</li>
</ol>
<p>This distinction is critical. As Parmenter notes, &ldquo;The term KPI has been misused for years. Most measures that organisations proudly call KPIs are simply performance indicators at best, and many are simply result indicators masquerading as KPIs&rdquo; (Parmenter, 2015).</p>
<h3 id="the-108010-rule">The 10/80/10 Rule</h3>
<p>Based on this taxonomy, Parmenter advocates for what he calls the &ldquo;10/80/10 rule&rdquo; for organisational measures:</p>
<ul>
<li>10 Key Result Indicators (KRIs) for the board</li>
<li>Up to 80 Result Indicators (RIs) and Performance Indicators (PIs) for management</li>
<li>10 Key Performance Indicators (KPIs) for staff</li>
</ul>
<p>This structured approach helps organisations focus on what truly matters while avoiding metric overload.</p>
<h2 id="the-seven-characteristics-of-true-kpis">The Seven Characteristics of True KPIs</h2>
<p>According to Parmenter (2015), genuine KPIs share seven essential characteristics:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Nonfinancial measures</strong>: Not expressed in dollars, euros, yen, etc.</li>
<li><strong>Measured frequently</strong>: Daily or weekly (not monthly or quarterly)</li>
<li><strong>Acted upon by senior management</strong>: Leadership demonstrates their importance</li>
<li><strong>Clear understanding</strong>: All staff understand the measure and what corrective action is required</li>
<li><strong>Ties to responsibility</strong>: Can be tied to a specific individual or team</li>
<li><strong>Significant impact</strong>: Affects multiple critical success factors</li>
<li><strong>Positive impact</strong>: Encourages appropriate action with minimal unintended consequences</li>
</ol>
<p>When evaluating potential KPIs, these characteristics provide a valuable litmus test. If a measure fails on multiple criteria, it&rsquo;s likely not a true KPI.</p>
<h2 id="common-kpi-mistakes-and-how-to-avoid-them">Common KPI Mistakes and How to Avoid Them</h2>
<h3 id="mistake-1-focusing-almost-exclusively-on-financial-metrics">Mistake 1: Focusing Almost Exclusively on Financial Metrics</h3>
<p>As noted by Robert Kaplan and David Norton in their Balanced Scorecard work (1996), &ldquo;Financial metrics tell you the results of decisions you made 1-3 months ago.&rdquo; They are inherently backward-looking.</p>
<p><strong>Solution</strong>: Parmenter recommends that true KPIs be nonfinancial measures that lead to financial results rather than simply measuring them. For example, measure customer satisfaction (leading indicator) rather than just revenue (lagging indicator).</p>
<h3 id="mistake-2-measuring-too-infrequently">Mistake 2: Measuring Too Infrequently</h3>
<p>According to Parmenter (2015), &ldquo;A monthly measure can never be a KPI&hellip; it&rsquo;s simply too old to be relevant for daily or weekly decision making.&rdquo;</p>
<p><strong>Solution</strong>: Create systems that allow for more frequent measurement of critical metrics. With modern technology, many previously monthly metrics can now be tracked weekly or even daily.</p>
<h3 id="mistake-3-setting-arbitrary-targets">Mistake 3: Setting Arbitrary Targets</h3>
<p>Many organisations set targets without understanding the measure&rsquo;s natural performance range, resulting in what statistician W. Edwards Deming called &ldquo;management by arbitrary numerical goal.&rdquo;</p>
<p><strong>Solution</strong>: Use statistical process control principles to understand natural variation before setting targets. Parmenter suggests at least 15 data points to establish a baseline.</p>
<h3 id="mistake-4-measuring-too-many-things">Mistake 4: Measuring Too Many Things</h3>
<p>A study by Bain &amp; Company found that companies with effective KPI systems measured fewer things—they were focused on what truly mattered (Marr, 2012).</p>
<p><strong>Solution</strong>: Apply Parmenter&rsquo;s 10/80/10 rule rigorously. For every new measure added, consider retiring an existing one.</p>
<h3 id="mistake-5-failing-to-distinguish-between-different-types-of-measures">Mistake 5: Failing to Distinguish Between Different Types of Measures</h3>
<p>As Parmenter says, &ldquo;When you call everything a KPI, you end up with a dysfunctional measurement system&rdquo; (Parmenter, 2015).</p>
<p><strong>Solution</strong>: Classify each measure using Parmenter&rsquo;s taxonomy and manage each type appropriately.</p>
<h2 id="implementing-parmenters-kpi-methodology">Implementing Parmenter&rsquo;s KPI Methodology</h2>
<h3 id="step-1-establish-critical-success-factors">Step 1: Establish Critical Success Factors</h3>
<p>Before defining KPIs, organisations must identify their critical success factors (CSFs)—the limited number of areas where satisfactory results will ensure successful performance.</p>
<p>Parmenter recommends a structured workshop approach to identify 5-8 organisational CSFs. These become the foundation for all performance measures.</p>
<h3 id="step-2-develop-balanced-set-of-performance-measures">Step 2: Develop Balanced Set of Performance Measures</h3>
<p>Building on Kaplan and Norton&rsquo;s Balanced Scorecard (1996) and Parmenter&rsquo;s refinements, measures should be balanced across six perspectives:</p>
<ol>
<li>Customer satisfaction</li>
<li>Financial performance</li>
<li>Learning and growth</li>
<li>Internal process efficiency</li>
<li>Employee satisfaction</li>
<li>Environment/community</li>
</ol>
<p>This balanced approach ensures no single aspect of performance is overemphasised at the expense of long-term sustainability.</p>
<h3 id="step-3-create-winning-kpis">Step 3: Create Winning KPIs</h3>
<p>Parmenter recommends a bottom-up approach to KPI development:</p>
<ol>
<li>Convene a cross-functional team to identify potential measures</li>
<li>Screen candidates against the seven KPI characteristics</li>
<li>Test selected measures for a pilot period</li>
<li>Refine based on feedback and observed impact</li>
<li>Formalise the final KPI set</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="step-4-develop-reporting-mechanisms">Step 4: Develop Reporting Mechanisms</h3>
<p>For KPIs to drive performance, they must be reported effectively. Parmenter advocates for:</p>
<ul>
<li>Daily or weekly dashboard updates</li>
<li>Exception-based reporting</li>
<li>Visual displays that highlight trends</li>
<li>Clear action thresholds</li>
</ul>
<p>As noted in his &ldquo;Winning CFO&rdquo; methodology (Parmenter, 2012), &ldquo;The reporting of performance measures should focus on exception reporting rather than a complete snapshot of all measures.&rdquo;</p>
<h3 id="step-5-facilitate-organisational-learning">Step 5: Facilitate Organisational Learning</h3>
<p>The final step is creating systems that encourage learning and improvement based on KPI results. This includes:</p>
<ul>
<li>Regular KPI review sessions</li>
<li>Root cause analysis of significant variations</li>
<li>Sharing of best practices across teams</li>
<li>Continuous refinement of metrics</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="examples-of-winning-kpis-vs-ineffective-measures">Examples of Winning KPIs vs. Ineffective Measures</h2>
<p>To illustrate the difference between true KPIs and less effective measures, consider these examples from Parmenter&rsquo;s work:</p>
<h3 id="traditional-metrics-vs-winning-kpis">Traditional Metrics vs. Winning KPIs</h3>
<p><strong>Financial Perspective:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Traditional: Monthly revenue (RI)</li>
<li>Winning KPI: Late shipments to key customers (measured daily)</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Customer Perspective:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Traditional: Quarterly customer satisfaction score (RI)</li>
<li>Winning KPI: Number of customer complaints yesterday (KPI)</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Internal Process Perspective:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Traditional: Monthly production efficiency (RI)</li>
<li>Winning KPI: Production line downtime in last 24 hours (KPI)</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Employee Perspective:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Traditional: Annual employee satisfaction (KRI)</li>
<li>Winning KPI: Staff suggestions implemented in past week (KPI)</li>
</ul>
<p>Note how the winning KPIs are measured more frequently and are more actionable than their traditional counterparts.</p>
<h2 id="case-study-transforming-kpis-at-a-manufacturing-company">Case Study: Transforming KPIs at a Manufacturing Company</h2>
<p><em>(Note: This case study is adapted from examples in Parmenter&rsquo;s publications)</em></p>
<p>A mid-sized manufacturing company struggled with performance measurement despite having over 100 metrics tracked monthly. After implementing Parmenter&rsquo;s methodology:</p>
<ol>
<li>They identified six critical success factors through facilitated workshops</li>
<li>Reduced their measurement set to 10 KRIs, 30 RIs/PIs, and 8 true KPIs</li>
<li>Moved key measures from monthly to daily/weekly tracking</li>
<li>Implemented visual management boards in each department</li>
<li>Established regular performance dialogues around the KPIs</li>
</ol>
<p>Results after six months:</p>
<ul>
<li>On-time delivery improved from 82% to 96%</li>
<li>Customer complaints reduced by 45%</li>
<li>Production efficiency increased by 15%</li>
<li>Employee suggestions implemented rose from 5 to 35 per month</li>
</ul>
<p>The key insight: By measuring fewer things but measuring them correctly, the organisation gained far more insight and impact.</p>
<h2 id="creating-a-kpi-implementation-roadmap">Creating a KPI Implementation Roadmap</h2>
<p>Based on Parmenter&rsquo;s &ldquo;Four Foundation Stones&rdquo; methodology (2015), here&rsquo;s a practical roadmap for implementing effective KPIs:</p>
<h3 id="foundation-stone-1-partnership-with-staff-unions-and-third-parties">Foundation Stone 1: Partnership with Staff, Unions, and Third Parties</h3>
<ul>
<li>Form a cross-functional KPI team</li>
<li>Involve frontline staff in measure selection</li>
<li>Train managers in performance coaching</li>
<li>Address concerns about measurement openly</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="foundation-stone-2-transfer-of-power-to-the-front-line">Foundation Stone 2: Transfer of Power to the Front Line</h3>
<ul>
<li>Push decision rights to where information exists</li>
<li>Create visual management systems</li>
<li>Establish action thresholds and response protocols</li>
<li>Empower teams to adjust processes based on KPI signals</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="foundation-stone-3-measure-and-report-only-what-matters">Foundation Stone 3: Measure and Report Only What Matters</h3>
<ul>
<li>Apply the 10/80/10 rule rigorously</li>
<li>Report different measures to different audiences</li>
<li>Focus on exception reporting</li>
<li>Use technology to automate data collection</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="foundation-stone-4-source-kpis-from-critical-success-factors">Foundation Stone 4: Source KPIs from Critical Success Factors</h3>
<ul>
<li>Identify organisational CSFs</li>
<li>Derive department and team CSFs</li>
<li>Align KPIs to these critical factors</li>
<li>Review alignment quarterly</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="the-financial-controllers-role-in-kpi-implementation">The Financial Controller&rsquo;s Role in KPI Implementation</h2>
<p>As financial controller, you have a unique opportunity to lead KPI transformation:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Education</strong>: Help the organisation understand the difference between various types of measures</li>
<li><strong>Facilitation</strong>: Lead workshops to identify CSFs and potential KPIs</li>
<li><strong>Integration</strong>: Connect KPIs to planning and budgeting processes</li>
<li><strong>Analysis</strong>: Provide insight into relationships between lead and lag indicators</li>
<li><strong>Technology</strong>: Champion systems that enable more frequent measurement</li>
</ol>
<p>As Parmenter notes in &ldquo;The Leading-Edge Manager&rsquo;s Guide to Success&rdquo; (2011), &ldquo;The finance team is uniquely positioned to lead performance measurement initiatives given their analytical skills and organisation-wide perspective.&rdquo;</p>
<h2 id="self-assessment-how-effective-are-your-current-kpis">Self-Assessment: How Effective Are Your Current KPIs?</h2>
<p>Evaluate your current measurement system against these criteria:</p>
<ol>
<li>Do your &ldquo;KPIs&rdquo; meet Parmenter&rsquo;s seven characteristics?</li>
<li>How frequently are your most important measures updated?</li>
<li>Can frontline staff explain how they influence key measures?</li>
<li>Do your measures balance across all six perspectives?</li>
<li>How many levels of approval are required to act on a KPI signal?</li>
<li>Do you distinguish between different types of measures?</li>
</ol>
<p>The more &ldquo;no&rdquo; answers you have, the greater opportunity for improvement using Parmenter&rsquo;s methodology.</p>
<h2 id="next-steps-for-your-kpi-journey">Next Steps for Your KPI Journey</h2>
<ol>
<li><strong>Audit current measures</strong>: Classify existing metrics into KRIs, RIs, PIs, and KPIs</li>
<li><strong>Workshop CSFs</strong>: Identify 5-8 organisational critical success factors</li>
<li><strong>Pilot better frequency</strong>: Select 2-3 metrics to measure more frequently</li>
<li><strong>Visual management</strong>: Create simple dashboards for team performance dialogues</li>
<li><strong>Review and refine</strong>: Establish a quarterly KPI review process</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Effective performance measurement isn&rsquo;t about more metrics—it&rsquo;s about better metrics. As Parmenter emphasises, &ldquo;Let&rsquo;s put time, effort, and money into measuring those activities that, when done well, will deliver the results we need&rdquo; (Parmenter, 2015).</p>
<p>By applying his systematic approach to KPIs, financial controllers can lead a transformation from measurement as a bureaucratic exercise to measurement as a performance driver.</p>
<p>In our next post, we&rsquo;ll explore how to translate these KPI principles into lean financial reporting that executives actually read and use for decision-making.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>Kaplan, R. S., &amp; Norton, D. P. (1996). <em>The Balanced Scorecard: Translating Strategy into Action</em>. Harvard Business School Press.</p>
<p>Marr, B. (2012). <em>Key Performance Indicators: The 75 Measures Every Manager Needs to Know</em>. Financial Times/Prentice Hall.</p>
<p>Neely, A., &amp; Bourne, M. (2020). <em>Why Measurement Initiatives Fail</em>. MIT Sloan Management Review.</p>
<p>Parmenter, D. (2011). <em>The Leading-Edge Manager&rsquo;s Guide to Success: Strategies and Better Practices</em>. John Wiley &amp; Sons.</p>
<p>Parmenter, D. (2012). <em>Winning CFOs: Implementing and Applying Better Practices</em>. John Wiley &amp; Sons.</p>
<p>Parmenter, D. (2015). <em>Key Performance Indicators: Developing, Implementing, and Using Winning KPIs (3rd ed.)</em>. John Wiley &amp; Sons.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>From Bean Counter to Business Partner</title><link>https://michaelbrunger.com/finance-bean-counter-to-business-partner/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://michaelbrunger.com/finance-bean-counter-to-business-partner/</guid><description>How to transform your role from traditional accounting to strategic business partnership</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-stereotype-vs-the-new-reality">The Stereotype vs. The New Reality</h2>
<p>For decades, finance professionals—particularly accountants and controllers—have battled the &ldquo;bean counter&rdquo; stereotype: detail-oriented, historically focused, compliance-driven, and somewhat disconnected from the operational realities of the business. This perception, while increasingly outdated, persists in many organisations.</p>
<p>As David Parmenter notes in his book &ldquo;The Leading-Edge Manager&rsquo;s Guide to Success&rdquo; (2011), &ldquo;Yesterday&rsquo;s finance team was renowned for producing financial information that was too late, too detailed, and not focused on what matters to the management team.&rdquo; This observation captures the fundamental challenge that modern financial controllers must overcome.</p>
<p>The new reality demands something entirely different:</p>
<p><strong>Bean Counter (Traditional Model)</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li>Focus on transactions and compliance</li>
<li>&ldquo;Scorekeeping&rdquo; mentality</li>
<li>Historical reporting</li>
<li>Technical accounting expertise</li>
<li>Risk aversion and control orientation</li>
<li>Process standardisation</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Business Partner (Modern Model)</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li>Focus on strategy and value creation</li>
<li>Forward-looking guidance</li>
<li>Predictive analysis and scenario planning</li>
<li>Broad business acumen</li>
<li>Balanced risk management perspective</li>
<li>Innovation and continuous improvement</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="parmenters-winning-finance-team-concept">Parmenter&rsquo;s &ldquo;Winning Finance Team&rdquo; Concept</h2>
<p>David Parmenter has been at the forefront of redefining the finance function&rsquo;s role. In his &ldquo;Winning CFO&rdquo; methodology (Parmenter, 2012), he emphasises that truly effective finance teams operate as partners to the business rather than merely as providers of financial information.</p>
<p>According to Parmenter, the winning finance team:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Sells the vision</strong>: Communicates the purpose behind finance initiatives</li>
<li><strong>Creates strategic alliances</strong>: Builds relationships across the organisation</li>
<li><strong>Maintains what&rsquo;s working</strong>: Preserves effective practices while innovating</li>
<li><strong>Understands the customers</strong>: Knows what internal customers genuinely need</li>
<li><strong>Delivers &ldquo;wow&rdquo; projects</strong>: Implements high-impact initiatives</li>
<li><strong>Uses leading-edge methodologies</strong>: Employs best practices in performance management</li>
</ol>
<p>This framework provides a valuable roadmap for controllers seeking to reposition themselves from technical specialists to strategic partners.</p>
<h2 id="the-four-faces-of-finance-leadership">The Four Faces of Finance Leadership</h2>
<p>Building on Parmenter&rsquo;s work, Deloitte&rsquo;s &ldquo;Four Faces of the CFO&rdquo; framework (Deloitte, 2021) offers another useful perspective on this evolution. While originally focused on CFO roles, it applies equally to controllers and finance managers:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Steward</strong>: Preserving assets, ensuring compliance</li>
<li><strong>Operator</strong>: Running efficient finance operations</li>
<li><strong>Strategist</strong>: Helping to shape overall strategy and direction</li>
<li><strong>Catalyst</strong>: Instilling a financial approach and mindset across the organisation</li>
</ol>
<p>Traditional controllers excel at the first two faces but must develop competencies in the latter two to truly function as business partners. As noted in Deloitte&rsquo;s research, high-performing finance teams spend approximately 60% of their time on strategist and catalyst activities, compared to just 30% for average teams.</p>
<h2 id="practical-steps-for-transformation">Practical Steps for Transformation</h2>
<h3 id="1-develop-business-acumen">1. Develop Business Acumen</h3>
<p>Business partnership requires understanding the business beyond its financial statements. As Parmenter emphasises in &ldquo;Winning CFO&rdquo; (2012), finance professionals need to &ldquo;walk in the shoes&rdquo; of operational colleagues:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Schedule regular operational visits</strong>: Spend time understanding how different departments function</li>
<li><strong>Learn the industry language</strong>: Master the terminology and metrics specific to your industry</li>
<li><strong>Study the value chain</strong>: Understand how your company creates and delivers value</li>
<li><strong>Know your customers</strong>: Gain insights into customer needs and behaviors</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="2-build-relationships-intentionally">2. Build Relationships Intentionally</h3>
<p>According to McKinsey&rsquo;s research on finance excellence (McKinsey &amp; Company, 2020), relationship-building is a critical yet often overlooked aspect of finance transformation:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Map your stakeholders</strong>: Identify key decision-makers and their priorities</li>
<li><strong>Establish regular touchpoints</strong>: Create structured opportunities for interaction</li>
<li><strong>Ask better questions</strong>: Focus on understanding business needs rather than just financial results</li>
<li><strong>Speak their language</strong>: Translate financial concepts into business terms</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="3-shift-from-reporting-to-analysis">3. Shift from Reporting to Analysis</h3>
<p>Parmenter advocates for a fundamental shift in how finance teams allocate their time. In &ldquo;Key Performance Indicators&rdquo; (Parmenter, 2015), he suggests:</p>
<ul>
<li>Reduce time spent on data compilation by 40-60%</li>
<li>Increase time spent on analysis by 30-50%</li>
<li>Focus reporting on exceptions and insights rather than comprehensive data</li>
</ul>
<p>This shift requires:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Automating routine processes</strong>: Implementing technology solutions for data collection and basic reporting</li>
<li><strong>Standardising analytics</strong>: Creating reusable frameworks for business analysis</li>
<li><strong>Developing forward-looking metrics</strong>: Building predictive models rather than just historical views</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="4-master-the-art-of-communication">4. Master the Art of Communication</h3>
<p>Business partners must communicate effectively. As Parmenter emphasises in his &ldquo;Winning KPIs&rdquo; methodology (2015), numbers without context rarely drive action:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Know your audience</strong>: Tailor information to the recipient&rsquo;s needs and preferences</li>
<li><strong>Focus on implications</strong>: Explain the &ldquo;so what&rdquo; behind the numbers</li>
<li><strong>Use visualisation effectively</strong>: Apply principles of data visualisation</li>
<li><strong>Tell stories with data</strong>: Frame information within relevant business narratives</li>
</ul>
<p>Research by the Corporate Executive Board (now Gartner) found that finance teams who effectively communicate insights are 24% more likely to be viewed as strategic partners.</p>
<h3 id="5-lead-change-initiatives">5. Lead Change Initiatives</h3>
<p>To be seen as a business partner, finance must actively drive improvement. In &ldquo;The Leading-Edge Manager&rsquo;s Guide to Success,&rdquo; Parmenter (2011) emphasises the importance of leading &ldquo;breakthrough projects&rdquo;:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Identify high-impact opportunities</strong>: Focus on initiatives with significant ROI</li>
<li><strong>Apply project management discipline</strong>: Demonstrate structured implementation capabilities</li>
<li><strong>Measure and communicate results</strong>: Quantify the value created</li>
<li><strong>Build on successes</strong>: Use completed projects as springboards for further initiatives</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="common-challenges-in-making-the-transition">Common Challenges in Making the Transition</h2>
<h3 id="challenge-1-the-technical-comfort-zone">Challenge 1: The Technical Comfort Zone</h3>
<p>Many finance professionals have built their careers on technical excellence. Stepping outside this comfort zone can be daunting.</p>
<p><strong>Solution</strong>: Start small by volunteering for cross-functional projects that allow you to apply financial expertise in a broader context while gradually developing new skills.</p>
<h3 id="challenge-2-credibility-gaps">Challenge 2: Credibility Gaps</h3>
<p>Operational colleagues may be skeptical of finance&rsquo;s ability to add value beyond compliance and control.</p>
<p><strong>Solution</strong>: As Parmenter suggests in &ldquo;Winning CFO&rdquo; (2012), begin with &ldquo;quick wins&rdquo; that demonstrate tangible value to build credibility for larger initiatives.</p>
<h3 id="challenge-3-time-constraints">Challenge 3: Time Constraints</h3>
<p>The daily pressures of financial operations can make it difficult to allocate time to strategic activities.</p>
<p><strong>Solution</strong>: Apply Parmenter&rsquo;s &ldquo;fast close&rdquo; methodology (2013) to streamline month-end processes, freeing up capacity for business partnering.</p>
<h3 id="challenge-4-skill-gaps">Challenge 4: Skill Gaps</h3>
<p>Business partnering requires capabilities that may not have been developed through traditional accounting training.</p>
<p><strong>Solution</strong>: Invest in targeted development in areas like strategic thinking, influence skills, and business acumen through both formal and experiential learning.</p>
<h2 id="measuring-your-progress">Measuring Your Progress</h2>
<p>How do you know if you&rsquo;re successfully making the transition from bean counter to business partner? Consider these metrics suggested by Parmenter and others:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Time allocation</strong>: % of finance team time spent on analysis vs. transaction processing</li>
<li><strong>Meeting invitations</strong>: Frequency of inclusion in strategic business discussions</li>
<li><strong>Decision impact</strong>: % of business decisions influenced by finance input</li>
<li><strong>Satisfaction surveys</strong>: Ratings from internal customers on finance&rsquo;s value contribution</li>
<li><strong>Initiative leadership</strong>: # of business improvement projects led by finance</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="case-study-finance-transformation-at-company-xyz">Case Study: Finance Transformation at Company XYZ</h2>
<p><em>(Note: This is an illustrative example based on Parmenter&rsquo;s work with clients as described in his publications)</em></p>
<p>A mid-sized manufacturing company found its finance team trapped in the traditional model—spending 80% of their time on transaction processing and reporting, with minimal time for analysis or business support.</p>
<p>Following Parmenter&rsquo;s methodology, they implemented several key changes:</p>
<ol>
<li>Automated standard reports using dashboard technology</li>
<li>Restructured the team to create dedicated business partner roles</li>
<li>Implemented a fast close process to complete month-end in 3 days</li>
<li>Established regular business review sessions with operational leaders</li>
</ol>
<p>The results were transformative:</p>
<ul>
<li>Time spent on reporting decreased from 60% to 30%</li>
<li>Analysis time increased from 15% to 45%</li>
<li>Internal customer satisfaction with finance increased by 40%</li>
<li>Finance-led initiatives delivered $1.2M in cost savings</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="self-assessment-where-are-you-on-the-journey">Self-Assessment: Where Are You on the Journey?</h2>
<p>To assess your current position on the bean counter to business partner spectrum, consider these questions:</p>
<ol>
<li>Do operational colleagues proactively seek your input on business decisions?</li>
<li>Can you clearly articulate your company&rsquo;s competitive strategy and market position?</li>
<li>Have you led or substantially contributed to a business improvement initiative in the past six months?</li>
<li>Do your reports focus more on insights and recommendations than data compilation?</li>
<li>How often do you spend time in operational areas of the business?</li>
<li>Can you explain complex financial concepts in non-technical language?</li>
</ol>
<p>The more &ldquo;yes&rdquo; answers you have, the further along you are in your transformation journey.</p>
<h2 id="action-items-for-your-first-90-days">Action Items for Your First 90 Days</h2>
<p>Based on Parmenter&rsquo;s &ldquo;first 100 days&rdquo; methodology for finance leaders (Parmenter, 2012), consider these priority actions:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Conduct a stakeholder analysis</strong>: Identify key business leaders and their priorities</li>
<li><strong>Schedule operational visits</strong>: Spend time understanding the business firsthand</li>
<li><strong>Review your reporting package</strong>: Identify opportunities for streamlining and insight enhancement</li>
<li><strong>Find a quick win</strong>: Identify and implement one high-visibility improvement</li>
<li><strong>Build your knowledge base</strong>: Dedicate time to understanding your industry and competitive landscape</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="conclusion-a-mindset-shift">Conclusion: A Mindset Shift</h2>
<p>The transformation from bean counter to business partner is fundamentally about mindset. As Parmenter emphasises throughout his work, it requires shifting from:</p>
<ul>
<li>Accuracy to relevance</li>
<li>Compliance to performance</li>
<li>Past to future</li>
<li>Data to insights</li>
<li>Control to enablement</li>
<li>Process to outcomes</li>
</ul>
<p>This journey won&rsquo;t happen overnight, but with deliberate focus and consistent action, you can reposition yourself and your team as valued strategic partners rather than mere financial technicians.</p>
<p>In our next post, we&rsquo;ll explore Parmenter&rsquo;s approach to Key Performance Indicators and how to develop metrics that actually drive performance rather than just measure it.</p>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<p>Deloitte. (2021). <em>Four Faces of the CFO</em>. Deloitte Development LLC.</p>
<p>McKinsey &amp; Company. (2020). <em>The CFO&rsquo;s Role in Helping Companies Navigate the Coronavirus Crisis</em>. McKinsey &amp; Company.</p>
<p>Parmenter, D. (2011). <em>The Leading-Edge Manager&rsquo;s Guide to Success: Strategies and Better Practices</em>. John Wiley &amp; Sons.</p>
<p>Parmenter, D. (2012). <em>Winning CFOs: Implementing and Applying Better Practices</em>. John Wiley &amp; Sons.</p>
<p>Parmenter, D. (2013). <em>Rapid Month-End Closing for Financial Managers</em>. Wiley-Global Finance.</p>
<p>Parmenter, D. (2015). <em>Key Performance Indicators: Developing, Implementing, and Using Winning KPIs</em>. John Wiley &amp; Sons.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Modern Financial Controller: Series Introduction</title><link>https://michaelbrunger.com/modern-financial-controller-series-introduction/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://michaelbrunger.com/modern-financial-controller-series-introduction/</guid><description>Introduction to the evolving role of financial controllers from technical accounting to strategic business partnership</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-evolution-of-finance-leadership">The Evolution of Finance Leadership</h2>
<p>When I earned my chartered accountant qualification, I envisioned a career focused primarily on technical accounting principles, financial reporting, and compliance. Fast forward to today, and the role of a finance manager has evolved into something far more dynamic and strategic than I could have anticipated. This transformation mirrors a broader shift in the finance profession—particularly for those in controller and finance manager positions.</p>
<p>The days of the financial controller as a mere &ldquo;bean counter&rdquo; are long behind us. Today&rsquo;s financial controllers are expected to be strategic partners, data analysts, risk managers, technology implementers, and forward-looking advisors. We&rsquo;re tasked not just with reporting what happened financially, but with providing insights that shape what <em>will</em> happen next.</p>
<h2 id="why-this-blog-series">Why This Blog Series?</h2>
<p>This blog series represents my commitment to &ldquo;learning in public&rdquo; as I navigate this evolving landscape. As a finance manager with a strong accounting foundation, I&rsquo;m documenting my journey of growth and discovery—synthesizing insights from thought leaders in the field, particularly David Parmenter, whose practical approaches to finance leadership have been revolutionary.</p>
<p>Through these posts, I aim to:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Distill key concepts</strong> from leading finance thinkers into practical, actionable advice</li>
<li><strong>Share implementation strategies</strong> that work in real-world scenarios</li>
<li><strong>Build a community</strong> of forward-thinking finance professionals</li>
<li><strong>Document my own transformation</strong> from technical accountant to strategic finance partner</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="who-is-david-parmenter">Who is David Parmenter?</h2>
<p>For those unfamiliar with his work, David Parmenter is a globally recognised expert in financial leadership, performance measures, and management reporting. His methodologies have transformed finance departments around the world, particularly through concepts like:</p>
<ul>
<li>Distinguishing between Key Result Indicators (KRIs) and genuine Key Performance Indicators (KPIs)</li>
<li>Implementing &ldquo;winning KPIs&rdquo; that actually drive organisational performance</li>
<li>Creating lean, focused reporting that executives actually use for decision-making</li>
<li>Transitioning from traditional budgeting to rolling forecasts</li>
<li>Developing &ldquo;fast close&rdquo; procedures that dramatically reduce month-end processing time</li>
<li>Building finance teams that function as true business partners</li>
</ul>
<p>Throughout this series, I&rsquo;ll be drawing extensively on Parmenter&rsquo;s frameworks while also incorporating insights from other thought leaders such as Jeremy Hope, Robin Fraser, Robert Kaplan, and Jack Stack.</p>
<h2 id="the-transformation-of-the-financial-controller-role">The Transformation of the Financial Controller Role</h2>
<p>The evolving expectations of financial controllers reflect broader changes in business:</p>
<p><strong>Traditional Controller Focus:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Historical reporting</li>
<li>Transaction processing</li>
<li>Compliance and control</li>
<li>Budget variances</li>
<li>Cost accounting</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Modern Controller Focus:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Strategic decision support</li>
<li>Business partnership</li>
<li>Performance optimisation</li>
<li>Predictive analytics</li>
<li>Technology enablement</li>
<li>Creating sustainable value</li>
</ul>
<p>According to a recent survey by McKinsey, companies with strong finance-business partnerships are 20% more likely to achieve breakthrough performance. Yet many finance departments struggle to make this transition effectively.</p>
<h2 id="what-to-expect-in-this-series">What to Expect in This Series</h2>
<p>Over the coming weeks, I&rsquo;ll be exploring:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>The strategic partner mindset</strong> and how to develop it</li>
<li><strong>Performance measurement systems</strong> that drive meaningful action</li>
<li><strong>Reporting transformation</strong> to deliver insights, not just information</li>
<li><strong>Beyond budgeting methodologies</strong> that increase agility</li>
<li><strong>Process improvements</strong> that free up time for value-added work</li>
<li><strong>Building high-performance finance teams</strong></li>
<li><strong>Leading business transformation</strong> from the finance office</li>
<li><strong>Technology enablement</strong> for modern finance functions</li>
</ol>
<p>Each post will combine theoretical frameworks with practical implementation steps, challenges you might face, and metrics to track your progress.</p>
<h2 id="my-learning-approach">My Learning Approach</h2>
<p>As I mentioned, this series is part of my &ldquo;learn in public&rdquo; journey. I&rsquo;m not presenting myself as the ultimate authority—rather, I&rsquo;m sharing what I&rsquo;m discovering as I implement these concepts in my own role.</p>
<p>I invite you to join me in this learning journey:</p>
<ul>
<li>Share your experiences in the comments</li>
<li>Suggest additional resources or experts I should explore</li>
<li>Challenge assumptions and offer alternative perspectives</li>
<li>Propose topics for deeper exploration</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="getting-started-self-assessment">Getting Started: Self-Assessment</h2>
<p>Before diving into the specific methodologies in future posts, I encourage you to consider where your finance function currently stands:</p>
<ol>
<li>What percentage of your finance team&rsquo;s time is spent on transaction processing versus business partnering?</li>
<li>Do your financial reports drive action, or do they simply communicate what happened?</li>
<li>How quickly can you close your books at month-end?</li>
<li>Does your budgeting process add value proportionate to the time invested?</li>
<li>Are your finance team members viewed as strategic advisors by operational colleagues?</li>
</ol>
<p>Your answers to these questions will help you identify which upcoming posts in this series might be most valuable for your situation.</p>
<h2 id="coming-up-next">Coming Up Next</h2>
<p>In our next post, we&rsquo;ll explore the specific mindset and skill shifts required to transition &ldquo;From Bean Counter to Business Partner&rdquo;—examining how traditional accounting expertise can be leveraged to provide strategic insights that drive business success.</p>
<p>I look forward to embarking on this journey with you as we transform our finance functions into the strategic powerhouses they have the potential to become.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>